<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Irenicum; or, An essay towards a brotherly peace &amp; union, between those of the congregational and presbyterian way; shewing out of the most learned and renowned divines of the congregational way, that their positions concerning 1. Church matters and members. 2. Church constitution and form. 3. Church state. 4. Church officers and ordination. 5. Church government and censures. 6. Church combinations and synods. 7. Communion with and separation from churches. are sufficient for the establishing a firme and lasting peace between them and the Presbyterians ... In pursuance of the good design begun at the Savoy, where it was agreed, and declared, that such reforming churches as consist of persons sound in the faith, and of conversation becoming the Gospel, ought not to refuse the communion of each other ... Drawn up and published by Discipulus de Tempore Junior.</title>
            <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E978_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 145:E978[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Irenicum; or, An essay towards a brotherly peace &amp; union, between those of the congregational and presbyterian way; shewing out of the most learned and renowned divines of the congregational way, that their positions concerning 1. Church matters and members. 2. Church constitution and form. 3. Church state. 4. Church officers and ordination. 5. Church government and censures. 6. Church combinations and synods. 7. Communion with and separation from churches. are sufficient for the establishing a firme and lasting peace between them and the Presbyterians ... In pursuance of the good design begun at the Savoy, where it was agreed, and declared, that such reforming churches as consist of persons sound in the faith, and of conversation becoming the Gospel, ought not to refuse the communion of each other ... Drawn up and published by Discipulus de Tempore Junior.</title>
                  <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
                  <author>D. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nathanael Webb and William Grantham, at the black Bear in Pauls Church-yard, near the little north-door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Discipulus de Tempore Junior = Matthew Newcomen.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: D.T.</note>
                  <note>The words "congregational and presbyterian" and "7. Communion with and separation from" are enclosed in brackets on title page; the words "1. Church matters .. separation from churches." are bracketed together.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IRENIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M;</hi> OR, AN ESSAY Towards a Brotherly PEACE &amp; VNION, Between thoſe of the
<list>
                  <item>Congregational And</item>
                  <item>Presbyterian</item>
               </list> Way;</p>
            <p>Shewing out of the moſt Learned and Renowned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the <hi>Congregational</hi> Way, that their Poſitions Concerning
<list>
                  <item>1. Church Matters and Members.</item>
                  <item>2. Church Conſtitution and Form.</item>
                  <item>3. Church State.</item>
                  <item>4. Church Officers and Ordination.</item>
                  <item>5. Church Government and Cenſures.</item>
                  <item>6. Church Combinations and Synods.</item>
                  <item>7. Communion with and Separation from Churches.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Are ſufficient for the eſtabliſhing a firme and laſting Peace between them and the Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>Drawn up and publiſhed by <hi>Diſcipulus De Tempore Junior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In purſuance of the good deſign begun at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> where it was agreed, and declared. <hi>That ſuch Reforming Churches as conſiſt of Perſons ſound in the Faith, and of Converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the Goſpel, ought not to refuſe the communion of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo far as may conſiſt,</hi> With their own principles reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, <hi>though they walk not in all things according to the ſame Rules of Church Order,</hi> Canon 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> and <hi>William-Grantham,</hi> at the black Bear in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the little North-door. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:2"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut who would write <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicums,</hi> ſeeing they who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it, reap (uſually) no other fruit, then he who running in between two men that are a fighting, with an honeſt intent to part them and make them friends, brings both their fiſts about his own ears, or turns both their ſwords into his own boſome, and maketh them both his enemies? at leaſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing party and he that thinks he hath
<pb facs="tcp:115279:3"/>the better of the cauſe, will take it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly ill, as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> do <hi>Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> which ſome of them call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <hi>Scotch</hi> non Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts the <hi>Irenicum</hi> of their Country man <hi>Forbes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of this made the Collector of theſe Papers, though often ſollicited with thoughts of that he hath now attempted, to lay them by, till be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little awakened, <hi>firſt</hi> with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of ſome thing towards an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation of diſſenting parties en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured, and (as they ſay) effected in <hi>Cumberland and Weſtmerland,</hi> and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Counties, and with an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome thing that was agreed by the Congregational way, in their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> that might conduce to that end, he judged it now ſeaſonable to preſent theſe Papers to publike view,
<pb facs="tcp:115279:3"/>that he might <hi>ſuum conferre ſymbolum;</hi> If this may procure a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and compoſing of the differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween brethren, the Collector hath his deſire and reward; if it fail and miſs that end, yet he hopes his reward is with the Lord, having this teſtimony in his own conſcience, that in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart he hath managed this cauſe not <hi>knowingly</hi> or <hi>willingly</hi> falſifyng and wreſting the words of thoſe reverend men whom he cites; from which crime if his own proteſtation be not enough to clear him, thou ſhalt by and by <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> have the depoſition of two ſufficient witneſſes. If thou wilt not believe them neither, get the Books and truſt thine own eyes. If any ſay theſe authors elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where expreſs themſelves otherwiſe; all that I anſwer, is, that my deſign and work was, not to reconcile them to
<pb facs="tcp:115279:4"/>themſelves, but if I could to their Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Brethren, which how far it is done read (but read with underſtanding and without prejudice) and then judge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord</hi> D. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="attestation">
            <head>The Atteſtation.</head>
            <p>WE have examined all the ſeveral Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here alledged, by the Books out of which they were taken, and finde them to be punctually and ſyllabically true; and that there is no falſification, nor violation of them; and this, we being perſons no wayes intereſted in the controverſies between the Presbyterian and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Brethren, nor engaged to either Party, Teſtifie under our hands.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. K. R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:4"/>
            <head>To the Judicious Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the manifold diviſions both in Church and State, whereby <hi>England</hi> hath been, and ſtill is damnified and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered; the doleful diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betwixt Presbyterians and Independants, are not the leaſt, nor leaſt lamented by gracious hearts, as in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; ſo becauſe the loud noiſe thereof, both from the Pulpit and the Preſs, doth cauſe their adverſaries ſinfully to rejoyce.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.20.</note> In this regard the Popiſh, the prophane, and Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical party do encourage their hopes, that the good work of Covenanted Church-Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> will ere long wither and come to nothing. True it is, that as neither kingdom nor houſe, ſo no other ſociety divided againſt it ſelf can ſtand;<note place="margin">Mark. 3.24, 25.</note> for diviſion maketh way for diſſipation.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.7.</note> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account in purſuance of that <hi>Machivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; impera;</hi> the Jeſuited
<pb facs="tcp:115279:5"/>Papiſt, and the ſelf-ſeeking Statiſt do vigorouſly endeavor to maintain and encreaſe our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of Religion at this day: errors and contentions which are like tares, hindring the growth of grace amongſt Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.23.</note> are ſowed by the Divel, their implacable enemy. And it is an expreſſion of great diſpleaſure from the Lord, when the evil ſpirit is ſent or ſuffered ſo far to prevail upon them which ſhould be one in mutual amity, that they in paſſion deal treacherouſly one with another.<note place="margin">Judg. 9.23.</note> As it cannot be denyed, but that animoſities cauſing ſad ſeparations, may be found amongſt good men (<hi>For the contention between</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas <hi>was ſo ſharpe that they departed aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one from the other</hi>) ſo experience amongſt our ſelves confirmeth,<note place="margin">Act. 15.39.</note> what <hi>Solomon</hi> long ſince aſſerted, <hi>A brother offended is harder to win than a ſtrong City, and their contentions are like the bars of a Palace.</hi> In the late Aſſembly of Divines called together by Authority of Parliament, many hours, yea days were run up in ſerious debates, that the Presbyterians and their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting brethren might be reconciled in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Church diſcipline. And ſince that time many books have been publiſh't by godly Miniſters of both; perſwaſions to drive on
<pb facs="tcp:115279:5"/>that good deſign, but the end intended hath not hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been accompliſht. Now the good hand of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, the God of Peace hath ſtirred up the heart of a faithful and able Miniſter of the Goſpel (whoſe name would adde authority to this work, though he ſee cauſe to conceal it) in a new way to attempt a brotherly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; His deſign is to ſtitch up our rents, and to heal our breaches by diſcovering the conceſſions and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the chief Patrons of the Congregational way, that in reference to Church conſtitution of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and officers, and in reference to Church admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations by Claſſes and Synods, there is not ſo great oppoſition betwixt the Presbyterians and them, as the Independent Brethren here amongſt us do pretend and publiſh. And let the indifferent Reader (who is not byaſſed with prejudice and partiality) judge whether there be not much ingenuity with meekneſſe of wiſdom, and ſolidity of judgement in the Narrative and inferences herein tendred, without any unbrotherly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections or bitter exaſperations. The whole Treatiſe both in regard of the matter and manner of managing it, ſpeaketh the Author to be a man of Peace. That this his undertaking might be the more ſucceſſeful, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth and improveth the judgement of thoſe Divines onely, whoſe parts and piety have rendred them emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, who alſo have publiſhed to the world their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions in this Controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Norton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shepherd,</hi> together with the Platform of Church-Government in <hi>N. Engl.</hi> which was atteſted by all the Elders convened in a National Aſſembly there; and becauſe the names of Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> are ſuperlatively famous in the Churches of Chriſt, therefore their judgement is moſt frequently inſiſted upon. During their abode in old <hi>England</hi> they were of
<pb facs="tcp:115279:6"/>one mind, heart, and way with the good old Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, who were real Presbyterians, ſo far as the Brethren of their moſt intimate acquaintance did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; and it is ſtrongly believed, that they would not have left their native Country for conſcience ſake, in caſe they might have been freed from the unſupportable yoak of Epiſcopal ſubſcription and conformity, whereof this may be a probable evidence that very few, if any Non-conformiſts of ſpecial note, who ſtayed in <hi>England,</hi> ever turned Independents. As for the moſt (if not all) of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Independents, they did at once ſtep o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the heads of Non-conformiſts, from conformity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Independency, or (as reverend Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> was wont with diſlike to expreſs it) they did at one jump leap out of the Surplice and Church Aſſemblies alſo. Our brethren of the <hi>Savoy</hi> Aſſembly, are too laviſh in nominating ſome worthy men, as favorites of their cauſe, for no other reaſon, yet appearing, but becauſe they were known Non-conformiſts. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> by appearing at the <hi>Hampton</hi>-court conference, diſcovered himſelf a friend unto Non-conformity, but he was ever oppoſite to them who made a Schiſm in or from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Dr. <hi>Chadderton</hi> alſo (a known Non-conformiſt, did diſlike ſeparation from the Church of <hi>England</hi>) Dr. <hi>Whittaker</hi> and Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> alſo were of his judgement. And it would be no hard task to undertake the nomination of many Non-conformiſts, who publikely in print have witneſſed their hearty diſlike of all wayes of ſeparation from the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>England,</hi> notwithſtanding the ſinful mixtures in them <hi>(vid.)</hi> Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> Mr. <hi>Travers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hilderſam,</hi> Maſter <hi>Dorrel,</hi> Maſter <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Maſter<note n="*" place="margin">Vide <hi>Mr.</hi> Balls <hi>anſwer to Mr.</hi> Cans <hi>book, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Separation from Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>Ball</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rathband;</hi> Mr. <hi>Hilderſam</hi> did much grieve when he underſtood that the Brethren in <hi>New
<pb facs="tcp:115279:6"/>England</hi> did depart from the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and he ſaid, This miſchief had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, if my counſel at Mr. <hi>Higginſons</hi> going over, had been taken; which was, that brethren driven thither by Epiſcopal perſecution, ſhould agree upon the Church Government, before they depart from hence. And it is well known, that many Presbyterian non-conformiſts, did by a letter ſent unto <hi>New England,</hi> bewaile their depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in practice (as they heard) from the way of Church government, which they owned here. As heretofore Mr. <hi>Parker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knew-ſtubs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Udall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sherwood,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Egerton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Balmford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Foord;</hi> and the many ſcores ſuſpended in <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> and K. <hi>James</hi>'s reign; ſo of later times, Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cleaver,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wight,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bourne,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pierſon;</hi> as alſo Mr. <hi>Hinde,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nicolds,</hi> Mr. <hi>Langley,</hi> (whom Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> mentioneth in his Defence of <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) as Non-conformiſts; Were Presbyterians, and utterly againſt even Semi-ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Unto theſe might be added Mr. <hi>John Paget,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pot,</hi> (Miniſters of the Reformed Engliſh Church at <hi>Amſterdam</hi>) and Mr. <hi>Hering,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Thomas Paget,</hi> their <hi>Succeſſors.</hi> The godly Miniſters of <hi>Scotland</hi> are generally Non-conformiſts; but the world knoweth, that they are Antagoniſts to Independency. And is it not probable, that if Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> had ſtayed in their Native Countrey, they would not have been at ſuch a diſtance from Church-fellowſhip with their Presbyterian Brethren, as old <hi>England</hi> Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are? For doubtleſs their conſcientious tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would have wrought them to practices anſwerable unto their judgement, held forth in this book. Theſe two Worthies all their life long were ſtudious and laborious in the Work of the Miniſtry, they were Patterns of Humility, Meekneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:115279:7"/>Love, ſelf-denial, and all pious practices in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Relations, and whole Converſation; By them Gods Ordinances publickly Adminiſtred, were highly prized, conſtantly frequented, and the Sabbath ſtrictly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as holy to the Lord. They neither covetouſly nor vain-gloriouſly ſought great things in the world by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing places of Honor, command and profit for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs. The life of faith, and the power of godlineſſe ſhined moſt gloriouſly in them, all their dayes; and how few in old <hi>England</hi> who boaſt of theſe Worthies as their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors in wayes of Independency, do merit ſuch a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of commendation, let them determin who are beſt acquainted with their converſation in their ſeveral ſtations and capacities, And when this book hath been ſeriouſly peruſed, let the Judicious Reader give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, whether in their Church-adminiſtrations, they be not ſo unlike unto them, that they muſt either diſclaim their Patronage, or change their preſent practices. It is a high commendation given of learned Mr. <hi>Calvine,</hi> that in his Inſtitutions, Commentaries, and other works, he doth <hi>ſibi conſtare,</hi> always agree with himſelf, whereas many others eſpecially ſuch who are much verſed in Polemical debates, do often croſs ſhins with themſelves through inconſiderateneſs or forgetfulneſs. This is not ſpoken to caſt reproach upon any good man, but to give an <hi>Item</hi> unto all, wiſely to weigh what they Puhliſh, and what they Practice. The Peace-makers are bleſſed, but <hi>thoſe that ſowe diſcord amongſt brethren, are an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 5.9. Prov. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>The wiſdom which is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated; Therefore follow peace and holineſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Love the truth and peace.</hi> Conſider what is ſaid,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 8.19.</note> and what may be ſuggeſted in this enſuing Treatiſe, and the Lord give a right underſtanding in all things.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115279:8"/>
            <head>An <hi>Advertiſement</hi> to the READER.</head>
            <p>LEt the <hi>Reader</hi> take notice? that theſe words in the ſecond line of the fourth page, <hi>Nations holy by Covenant, therefore Churches:</hi> and theſe words in the fifteenth line of the ſame page; <hi>and according to this ſenſe may we not ſay</hi> Saint <hi>Saul,</hi> Saint <hi>Demas,</hi> Saint <hi>Judas? and that a Church made up of ſuch as theſe, is a Church of Saints?</hi> Both theſe ſentences ſhould have been put in the <hi>margent,</hi> being not the words of the Reverend <hi>Author</hi> there cited, but <hi>Obſervations</hi> which the Collector conceived he might juſtly make upon his words.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115279:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>IRENIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> OR, AN ESSAY Towards a Brotherly PEACE and UNION,</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the matter of a Church under the New Teſtament, and who are fit to be Church-members.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. I.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is the matter of a Church now in the New Teſtament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſiſted of no other matter, than of ſuch as profeſſed the faith of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of their ſeed; and the Church of the New Teſtament conſiſteth of the like. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Baptiſm, page.</hi> 132. <hi>line</hi> 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Who then may be admitted, or accounted members of the Church in the New Teſtament, and who not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ignorant, perſons that are groſly ignorant of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115279:9"/>firſt principles and foundations of Religion, are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived members into the Church; or if born in the Church, yet ſo continuing in their ignorance to their ripe age, are not to be confirmed members, <hi>That is, they are not to be admitted to the ſeal of the Lords Supper, and ſo are not to be admitted to other rights of a Church-member, as election of officers, admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of members, cenſure of offenders,</hi> &amp;c. Mr. Cotton, Holineſs of Church-members, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. <hi>line</hi> 32.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Atheiſts, Witches, Papiſts, and all Hereticks, who either deny the faith, or profeſs a falſe faith againſt the foundation of Chriſtian Religion, they are not to be received members into the Church, without reformation and repentance. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Notorious perſons, ſcandalous for any groſs crime, as Idolatry, Adultery, Fornication, Drunkenneſs, Oppreſſion, Perjury, Profaneneſs, Lying, are not to be received into the Church, or not continued in it. <hi>Ibi. pag.</hi> 20. <hi>line</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Yea, but if a man be not tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly converted and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, is not that enough to make him uncapable of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, though he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> neither groſly ignorant, nor notoriouſly ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Irregeneration alone doth not keep any from Church fellowship,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> unleſs it be accompanied with ſuch fruits as are openly ſcandalous, and do convincingly manifeſt unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as groſs ignorance, palpable hypocriſie or ſuch like ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wickedneſſes. Mr. <hi>Cotton, Holineſs of Church-members, p.</hi> 92. <hi>line</hi> 35. And therefore though it be comfortable and deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the admiſſion of members into the Church, when the whole Church and all the members thereof are ſatisfied in the ſincerity of the regeneration of ſuch who are to be received, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the firſt planting or gathering of Churches: yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in judgement nor in practice do we ſuſpend their admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till we be convinced in our conſciences of the certain and unfallible ſignes of their regeneration. Mr. <hi>Cotton, holineſſe of Church members, p.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> ult. And as for that the Members ſhould at ſeveral times in ſeveral companies repair to thoſe that are to be admitted to examine the time and manner of their conversion; I am afraid it is a preſumed kind of liberty, which wants precept and example for any thing that ever appeared to me in the Scripture. Mr. <hi>Hooker Survey of Diſcipline, part</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115279:9"/>Object. 1. <hi>But is it not ſaid,</hi> John 3.3, 5. except a man be born again of water and of the Holy Ghoſt, he cannot enter into the kingdom of heaven; <hi>therefore he cannot be admitted into the Church (for that is the kingdom of heaven) except he be regenerate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the kingdom of heaven there is meant, not the Church of God, but the ſtate of glory. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Baptiſm, pag.</hi> 139. <hi>line</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>But it is ſpoken of the new Hieruſalem,</hi> Rev. 21.27. <hi>which is the Goſpel-Church, that no unclean thing ſhall enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into; therefore no unregenerate perſon ought to be admitted into the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That text is a part of the deſcription of the pure Church of the Jews after their laſt converſion called the new Hieruſalem, by the condition of ſuch Proſelites as from among the Nations ſhall enter into fellowſhip with them; they ſhall not be prophane perſons, corrupters and defilers of others, nor makers of images, which are abominations and lyes: and that the deſcription agreeth to infants <hi>(though unregenerate)</hi> as well as to others. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant bapt. p.</hi> 133. <hi>l.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>But is there not more required to Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, then that a man be neither ignorant nor ſcandalous? Is there not poſitive holineſſe required? why elſe are the members of the Churches in the New Teſtament, ſo frequently called Saints?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Saints by external calling as diſtinct from Saints by internal calling, are the true matter of the viſible Church. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline, part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 21. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Who then are Saints by external calling?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are three ſorts of holineſs; one by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation from Chriſt; a ſecond by regeneration from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; a third by ſeparation to God and his worſhip, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Ordinances through the Covenant; many enjoy this laſt holineſs though they do not enjoy the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant baptiſme, p.</hi> 125. <hi>line</hi> 1. And they may be holy by covenant, who are not yet holy by the ſpirit of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 67. <hi>line</hi> 30. and they w ho believe with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary or hiſtorical faith onely, may be holy by covenant. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 28. And the covenant of grace is holy, becauſe it gives
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115279:10"/>right to holy priviledges, and denominates them holy, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons, families, or Nations, nations holy by covenant, therefore Churches, thoſe whom God calls to ſuch covenant with himſelf. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant bapt.</hi> for it ſeparates them from other people, and ſets them apart to the Lord, and his holy worſhip, as it is <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6, 7, 8. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 111. <hi>line</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>But can any be ſaid to be in or belong unto the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, but thoſe that are in the ſtate of grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a twofold ſtate of grace; one adherent, which ſome not unfitly call federal grace, ſanctifying to the purifying of the fleſh, <hi>Heb</hi> 9.13. the other inherent, ſanctifying the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man. And of this there are two ſorts, one whereby per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in covenant are ſanctifyed by common graces which makes them ſerviceable and uſeful in their callings (as <hi>Judas, Demas,</hi> and ſuch like hypocrites; and according to this fence may we not ſay Saint <hi>Saul,</hi> Saint <hi>Demas,</hi> Saint <hi>Judas?</hi> and that the Church made up of ſuch as theſe, is a Church of Saints?) The other whereby perſons in covenant are ſanctified unto union and communion with Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant baptiſme p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>Now though all that are in the Church be not ſanctified and in the ſtate of grace in this laſt and ſtricteſt fence, yet in the two former they may.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>But ſeeing faith is the condition of the covenant, are not all who believe not excluded from the covenant? and muſt they not firſt come to faith before they can come to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There is no place proves all are excluded from the outward diſpenſation of the Covenant, but Believers onely, Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant baptiſm p.</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 12. If the covenant were onely to them that believe, then the faith whereby we believe, is not given to any by the covenant. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>If the Church conſiſts onely of real Saints; then real ſanctifying grace is never given to any in the Churchy but alwayes in the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not firſt faith, and then to the covenant; but firſt the covenant, and then faith written and wrought in the heart by the ſpirit to fulfill the covenant. Mr. <hi>Cotton f infant baptiſme, page.</hi> 54. <hi>line</hi> 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115279:10"/>Queſt. 8. <hi>But is not mens conſent to and acceptance of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, neceſſary to the bringing them into covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gods appointment makes a covenant, whether the creature aſſent to the agreement or no. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant baptiſme, pag.</hi> 64. <hi>line</hi> 35.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>But yet men muſt have faith before they can be in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, muſt they not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The children of the faithful are not firſt converted, and ſo come under the Covenant; but firſt under the Covenant, and ſo come to be converted. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 29. <hi>line</hi> 7. God did eſtabliſh his Covenant with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 17.21. yet it doth not appear that <hi>Iſaac</hi> had any faith then, much leſſe was. it viſible. <hi>Idem. page</hi> 33. <hi>line pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle expounds the Covenant, as given not only to them who are converted, and ſo brought on to believe, but to them who yet want faith and converſion; <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25, 26. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 34. <hi>line</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>But is not the admitting of ſuch, who have no true faith nor ſaving grace, to be Church-Members, and to have right to the Covenant; is it not a diſhonour to God and Jeſus Christ? Doth it not make Christ the head of an hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogeneal body, and to have members unſutable to himſelf, a living head and dead members? ſurely Christ will admit of no ſuch members; Will any man admit of dead branches to be ſet in his Vineyard?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is true, the Church which is the myſtical body of Chriſt, ought to be ſutable to Chriſt her head, and ſo ſhe is many times, but not alwayes every Member, yea, very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome every Member, if at any time. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 102. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>It is utterly untrue to ſay that Chriſt admits not of any dead Plants to be ſet in his Vineyard; or that he takes not to himſelf a compounded body of living and dead Members, or that the Church of God is not a mixed company, &amp;c. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though no man will admit of dead Plants to be ſet in his Vineyard, or grafted in his ſtock, yet many Plants that are grafted and ſet may prove dead. Men indeed will not admit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115279:11"/>dead Plants to be grafted or ſet, becauſe they know not what to do with them when they are dead: But if dead Plants after they are grafted, would grow either to be fruitful, or if not fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, good fire-wood, it would be no bad husbandry to ſet and graft dead Plants. And ſo it is here, God thinks it no bad huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in him to admit dead Plants to be ſet, and grow in his Vineyard; and if they grow fruitful, well; if not, to tolerate them there till they grow up to fulfill their iniquity, as he did the Jews, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.32. becauſe he knows then how to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the glory of his juſtice, <hi>in caſting them into the fire of hell,</hi> John 15.6. Matth. 3.10. <hi>Idem, page</hi> 101. <hi>line</hi> 31.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Dead perſons if in Covenant, are alive to God, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.77, 38. And though a twig cannot receive life from the ſtock, unleſſe it bring life with it before it be engraffed, yet Chriſt can give life to dead branches that are put to him, as well as the dead Corps of <hi>Eliſha</hi> could give life to the dead man caſt into his grave, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.21. <hi>Idem, page</hi> 150. <hi>line</hi> 13, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>But will Chriſt being ſpiritual, endure a natural wife?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſay he will not, were to charge Chriſt himſelf with folly and with indignity offered to himſelf, that he being ſpiritual, ſhould take ſo many thouſand Infants into Covenant with him, who for the moſt part are natural; for one that is born of the Spirit, there are twenty born of the fleſh. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 160. <hi>line</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Beſides, though Chriſt by taking a company to be a Church unto himſelf, doth enter into a Marriage-Covenant with them, yet not into Marriage-Covenant with each Member at firſt. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>May any man be admitted a Member of the Church, but upon profeſſion of his faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Profeſſion of faith and repentance is required from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts of grown years, whether Jews or Pagans. Mr. <hi>Cotton of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Bapt. page</hi> 154. <hi>line</hi> 12. <hi>But as for thoſe that are born with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church, and have been baptized in their infancy,</hi> Baptiſme is a Sacrament ſealing unto them, as other ſpiritual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, ſo their initiation into Church-memberſhip. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Holineſſe of Church Members, page</hi> 96. <hi>line</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115279:11"/>Queſt. 13. <hi>But ſeeing ſome are to be admitted upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, and you ſaid before that a man may be a Church Member and in Covenant, that hath but a tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or hiſtorical faith; if you put ſuch a man upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his faith, do you not cauſe him to diſſemble and lye, and play the hypocrite?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True or falſe profeſſion may be attended either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the doctrine of faith profeſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or in reſpect of the grace of faith profeſſing it, if the profeſſion of the doctrine of faith be true, though the grace of fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th in the profe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or of it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. Or it may be hypocritical and falſe, yet we dare not deny the nature and power of a Church to ſuch. As the Church judgeth not of hidden crimes, ſo neither doth the faithful Judge, of the Churches by their hidden hypocriſie, but by their open ſcandals in doctrine or life. God would have his people live without anxious perplexity, <hi>as in marriage,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.32. ſo in every ſociety. It were an inextricable perplexity to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the eſſence and validity of Churches and Church Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations upon the hidden ſincerity of Churches, and Church-Officers or Members. Mr. <hi>Cottons way of the Churches clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 40. <hi>line</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> makes it moſt probable that there is no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church wherein the profeſſion of the true faith doth take place, but there are ſome found that are true believers in the ſame place. <hi>Ibid. page</hi> 91. <hi>line</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>But is it not a dangerous thing to account wicked men and hypocrites Church Members, and in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? Doth it not harden them in their ſinnes, and make them promiſe themſelves life in the way they are in, and keep them from returning from their evil wayes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not promiſe life to any by the Covenant, unleſſe they be Elect; and becauſe though they be Elect, yet that is unknown to them, and till they repent and believe, we tell them they cannot partake in the ſaving benefits of the Covenant till they be regenerate, and quickned by the Spirit, as Chriſt told <hi>Nicodemus.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 33. <hi>line</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>But God approves and receives none but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, Heb.</hi> 11.6. Without faith k is impoſſible to pleaſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115279:12"/>God; <hi>and how can the Church approve or receive any whom God doth not approve and receive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. ſhews that no man can be accepted of God <hi>without faith;</hi> but not that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive any into outward fellowship of the Covenant without faith. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Baptiſme. page</hi> 57. <hi>line</hi> 31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God may approve a man to be admitted into the Covenant, whoſe perſon he approves not. Mr. <hi>Cotton, Infant Bapt. page</hi> 66. <hi>line</hi> 39.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For it is one thing for the Word of God to approve men to be in Covenant, another thing to approve them in the Covenant. God he did never approve <hi>Saul</hi> nor <hi>Jehu</hi> in their Kingdome, yet he approved both ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Kingdome. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 68. <hi>line</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But is it not ſaid,</hi> John 4. <hi>that God ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him,</hi> as worſhip him in Spirit and truth? <hi>therefore none but ſuch may be admitted to the Ordinances of God. And is it not ſaid, Acts</hi> 2.47. the Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved, or ſaved men, <hi>as ſome tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it? therefore none but ſuch as are in the ſtate of grace and ſalvation, ſhould be added to the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſaid God ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, <hi>as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and in truth;</hi> but it is not ſaid God findeth ſuch in every Church. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Baptiſme. page</hi> 103. <hi>line</hi> 35. <hi>Much leſſe none but ſuch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>The Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved; but it is not ſaid he added none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> Were not <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphyra</hi> added to the Church, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> alſo, who yet for ought appears, were none of them ſaved? Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. page</hi> 67. <hi>line</hi> 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object. But as none inviſibly before God are by him appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at all to have right to any priviledges of grace, but only as he looketh upon them in his Sonne: No more are there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny before man viſibly to be approved of, ſo as to have right to the ſame, but as they appear to be in Chriſt by ſome effect of faith declaring the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115279:12"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you mean by grace, ſaving grace, it is true, none have right to any priviledge of ſaving grace,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> but as God looks at them in his Son, either by faith or by election unto faith; if you mean by grace the outward diſpenſation of the covenant of grace and of the ſeal thereof, it is true none have right to any priviledge of the covenant or the ſeal of it, but as they are in Chriſt, either by faith or by election unto faith, or by the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the Church, whereof Chriſt is the head; in which reſpect all the members of the Church and their ſeed are in Chriſt, as branches in the vine or olive, and may be cut off for want of faith to make them fruitful in him. Mr. <hi>Cotton of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant bapt. p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But when you ſay none have right to the covenant or the external priviledges thereof, but as they appear to be in Chriſt by ſome effect of faith declaring the ſame, that you cannot make good from Scripture-light. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant bapt. p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of Church matter and Church-members. Now out of this that hath been ſpoken, I draw theſe plain poſitions with ſome inferences.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Church of the old Teſtament and new do not differ one from another in the qualification of their matter and members. <hi>See the anſwer to the firſt queſtion.</hi> Therefore the Church of the old Teſtament conſiſted of viſible Saints as well as the Church of the new.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sole want of grace doth not make a man uncapable of Church-memberſhip, unleſs ignorance and ſcandal do accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it. <hi>See the anſwer to the ſecond and third queſtion.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man may be denyed memberſhip, becauſe it doth not appear to the Church in the beſt judgement of charity and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion thar he hath true ſaving grace.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The members of the viſible Church are Saints in reſpect of outward calling, not inward inherent grace. <hi>See anſwer to the four th queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The holineſs from which the members of the viſible Church are denominated Saints, is not by imputation or rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115279:13"/>but by ſeparation to God and his worſhip. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 5. According to which <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Demas</hi> may be denominated Saints. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 6. Therefore all aſſemblies of people thus ſet apart to the worſhip of God, are Churches of Saints, and one Church may not ſay unto another, ſtand apart from me, for I am holyer then thou.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The covenant of grace ſeparates men and women from other people, ſets them apart to the Lord and his holy worſhip, gives them right to holy priviledges, denominates them holy, or Saints. <hi>See the anſwer to the fifth queſtion.</hi> Therefore the covenant of grace (and not any other) conſtitutes the Church and gives Church memberſhip.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Neither faith nor conſent to the covenant is neceſſary to the bringing of men outwardly into covenant. <hi>See the anſwer to queſt.</hi> 7, 8. Therefore an explicite conſent is not required to the conſtituting of a Church.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The covenant of grace is applied to men, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have faith and are converted, but that they may have faith and be converted. <hi>See anſwer to queſtion</hi> 7. <hi>and</hi> 9. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by a like reaſon men are to be admitted members of the Church, not onely becauſe they have faith and are converted, but that they may have faith and be converted; for the Church and the covenant are commenſurate.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Though Chriſt be a living head, yet he counts it no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to him to admit of dead members in his Church, which is his myſtical body, as knowing how to glorifie himſelf in or by dead members. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 10. And though Chriſt be ſpiritual, yet he doth not deſpiſe to take into covenant with himſelf thoſe that are but natural. <hi>See the anſwer to the</hi> 11. <hi>queſt.</hi> Therefore they arrogate to themſelves to be wiſer and holyer then Chriſt himſelf, who deſpiſe and depart from Church aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and communion, becauſe of the mixture of thoſe which are not ſpiritual and have nor the life of grace.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Chriſt though he be married to the Church, is not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly married to every member of the Church. <hi>See anſwer to queſtion</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Profeſſion of faith in order to admiſſion unto Church-memberſhip is onely required of thoſe that from Judaiſm and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115279:13"/>Paganiſm are converted unto Chriſt, and not from ſuch as being born in the Church are admitted in their infancy; for their baptiſm ſeals to them their initiation into Church-memberſhip. <hi>See anſwer to queſtion</hi> 12. Therefore it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done to any that have been baptized in their infancy, to deny them admiſſion into the Church, unleſſe they make a profeſſion of their faith, and that before the whole Church.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. It is not the grace of faith, but the doctrine of faith, the profeſſion whereof is required in Church-members. <hi>See anſwer to queſtion</hi> 13. Therefore it is irregular to put people upon the relation of the time and manner of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. It were an inextricable perplexity to ſuſpend the eſſence and validity of Churches and Church adminiſtrations upon the hidden ſincerity of Churches, Church Officers, or members. <hi>See anſwer to queſtion</hi> 13. Therefore they make deſperate ſnares for their conſciences and the conſciences of others, that ſay none may be Officers or members of a Church, but ſuch as are really converted ones.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. God approved <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jehu</hi> to be admitted to their kingdom, though he did not approve their perſons or way of adminiſtring their kingdom. <hi>See the anſwer to queſtion</hi> 15. So (by a parity of reaſon we may conclude that) God approves ſome men to be admitted officers or members of the Church, whoſe perſons and wayes he doth not approve.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. It cannot be made good by Scripture-light, that none have right to the covenant and external priviledges thereof, but as they appear to be in Chriſt by ſome effect of faith declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame. <hi>See anſwer to the last queſtion.</hi> Therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject any for want of evidence of faith, is not warrantable by the word.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115279:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Form and conſtitutions of a Church.</head>
               <p>Queſtion 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHether had the Church of</hi> England <hi>ever a true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſay that the Church of <hi>England</hi> never had any true conſtitution,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> is a raſh and a falſe ſpeech; raſh, for can you ſay it, or do you know it becauſe you were then born? or becauſe the number of your dayes is great? as God queſtioneth with <hi>Job</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Iob</hi> 38.21. Or have you found ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by reading of ancient records and ſtories? If you dare cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit them (as doubtleſs they are more worthy of credit that lived near thoſe times, and had the view of antient records, then ſome of your later books, who ſpeak either out of partiality to <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Jeſuites; or out of prejudice againſt the ſtate of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſome rigid Separatiſts do.) But thoſe antient records will tell you that <hi>England</hi> received the faith of Chriſt, by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of thoſe primitive Apoſtolick Saints, who doubtleſs plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches not after the pattern of Antichriſt, but after the manner of the Apoſtles. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant Baptiſm; pag.</hi> 186. <hi>line</hi> 3. <hi>Therefore to ſay the Church of</hi> England <hi>never had a true conſtitution, is not onely raſh but falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> for the Churches of <hi>England</hi> were rightly gathered and planted at the firſt. Mr. <hi>Cottons way of the Church, pag.</hi> 111. <hi>line</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>But have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Churches of</hi> England <hi>been wofully corrupted ſince by Antichriſtian uſurpations and innovations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Yes; yet that did not caſt them into a worſe eſtate than the ten tribes in Iſrael under <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and his ſucceſſors, eſpecially under <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſabel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and the time ſucceeding them when yet God owned them for his Church, and their circumciſion was not a nullity. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. pag.</hi> 187. <hi>line</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For the Church now in being, moſt of their members had their admiſſion into the Church ſealed in Baptiſm.</hi> For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115279:14"/>children are born in the Church, to whom the paſtor is by office a Paſtor, and whoſe converſion he is bound to attend and intend. Mr. <hi>Cotton of holineſſe of Church-members, pag.</hi> 51. <hi>line</hi> 21. And their baptiſm ſeals to them their initiation into Church-memberſhip. <hi>Ibi. pag.</hi> 96. <hi>line</hi> 31.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>But they who are now Church-members, were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized upon the account of the baptiſm of their forefathers; and they (that is their forefathers) were bap ized under Antichriſt, and ſo their baptiſm was a ſtone lying in Antichriſts foundation; and how can this give right of admiſſion into the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The baptiſm of believers and of their ſeed, is no more a ſtone lying in Antichriſts foundation, then is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in one God, into which we and our children are baptized. That and other Goſpel-ordinances, they were in <hi>Rome</hi> but as the veſſels of the temple were in <hi>Babylon</hi> reſerved for the uſe of the Church after their return. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant baptiſm, pag.</hi> 163. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>But to the true and right constitution of a Church, entring into covenant is neceſſary, is it not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 That was done in King <hi>Edward</hi> and Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> days;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and whereas they ſay our Church is but a Parliament conſtitution, that doth not weaken but eſtabliſh our Church. Mr. <hi>Cotton on the</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt. of Iohn,</hi> 2 <hi>chap.</hi> 19 <hi>verſ. page</hi> 157. <hi>line</hi> 43, 44, <hi>amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſubſtance of the Church conſtituting covenant is ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t where there is a real agreement and conſent of a company of faithful perſons to meet conſtantly together in one Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the publike worſhip of God, and their mutual edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which agreement and conſent they do expreſs by their conſtant practice of coming together for the publike worſhip of God, and Religious ſubjection to the Ordinances of God: <hi>Their Platform of Church diſcipline agreed upon by the Elders and meſſengers of the Churches in New England, chap.</hi> 4. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The people in the Pariſhes of <hi>England,</hi> where there is a Miniſter put upon them by the Patron or Biſhop, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly hold them to the fellowſhip of the people of ſuch a place, attend all the Ordinances there uſed, and the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115279:15"/>of the Miniſter ſo impoſed upon them, ſubmit thereunto, perform all ſervices that may give countenance and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his perſon in the work of his Miniſtry. By ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and a fixed attendance upon all ſuch ſervices they declare that <hi>(conſent and covenant)</hi> by their practice which others do hold forth by publike profeſſion. Mr. <hi>Hooker Survey of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 47. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>What then is the work that is now to do in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The work which is now to do in the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is not to make Churches where there were none,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to their firſt primitive inſtitution. Mr. <hi>Cotton way of the Churches, pag.</hi> 151. <hi>line ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of the conſtitution and form of a Church: Now out of this I ſhall alſo draw ſome few plain poſitions, with ſome inferences.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſay that the Church of <hi>England</hi> never had a true conſtitution, is a raſh and falſe ſpeech. <hi>See chapter</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer to the firſt question.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Antichriſtian uſurpations and innovations that have overgrown the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have not nullified the firſt conſtitution of it. <hi>See chapter</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer to queſtion</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The baptiſm adminiſtred and received in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is no more Antichriſtian then the doctrine of the Trinity. <hi>See chapter</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer to question the third.</hi> Therefore they are condemned who refuſe to be preſent in our aſſemblies, when baptiſme is adminiſtred.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Not onely baptiſme, but other Goſpel-Ordinances were reſerved in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the uſe of the Church in after times, as the veſſels of the temple in Babylon. <hi>See chap.</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer to queſt.</hi> 3. Thence quere, why not ordination reſerved there for the Churches uſe as well as baptiſm, and yet no more Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian then baptiſm.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The engaging of the people to reformation by <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> had the vertue of a covenant to conſtitute the Church. <hi>See Chapter ſecond, anſwer to queſtion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115279:15"/>the fourth.</hi> Therefore much more the late ſolemn league and covenant.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Peoples ordinary and fixed attending together upon one Miniſtery, and joyning ordinarily together in the duties of publike worſhip, hath the nature and vertue of a Church cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. <hi>See chap.</hi> 2. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 4. And therefore they who moſt urge the neceſſity of a covenant, cannot condemn our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial aſſemblies as no Churches for want of ſuch a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The work now to do in <hi>England,</hi> is not to make Churches where none are, but to reduce them to their primitive inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>See chap.</hi> 2. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 5. Therefore they who have troubled themſelves and the Church ſo much with conſtituting and gathering new Churches, have troubled themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with a work they have nothing to do withall; and ſo have cauſe to fear that the Lord Chriſt will ſay unto them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, Who hath required this at your hands?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Church State.</head>
               <p>Queſtion 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat think you of the Aſſemblies and Congregations of</hi> England?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The faithful Congregations in England are true Churches of Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Hooker Survey of diſcipline, preface a</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>But what is meant by faithful congregations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There is the nature of a true viſible Church, where the word of God is purely preached,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> the Sacraments duely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, with diſcipline alſo according to the word of God. But then the Sacrament muſt not be adminiſtred to undue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſuch as are the ignorant and ſcandalous; nor the ignorant and ſcandalous muſt not be admitted into the Church, if diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline be rightly adminiſtred; yea though all theſe do not concur joyntly, yet the eſſence of a true Church may be found,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115279:16"/>though defective for integrity. Mr. <hi>Cotton, Holineſſe of church-members, pag.</hi> 10. <hi>line</hi> 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For where there hath been a Church that hath yeelded profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſpel of Chriſt, then in caſe a ſettled Miniſtry be continued there, God ſtill continues a true viſible Church there. Mr. <hi>Cotton holineſs of Church-members, pag.</hi> 5. <hi>line</hi> 12. And the eſſence of a true viſible Church is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved though there be found in it ſome hypocrites and ſome notoriouſly ſcandalous both in judgement and practice. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton holineſs of Church-members, p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither doth the hypocriſie of ſundry members of the Church, and the toleration of ſome open ſcandals preſently take away the nature of the Church. Mr. <hi>Cotton, holineſs of Church-members, pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For the members of the Church though orderly conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, may in time grow corrupt, which though they ought not to be tolerated in the Church, yet their continuance therein, through the defect of the execution of diſcipline and Church-cenſures, doth not immediately diſſolve the being of the Church, as appears in the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Galatia, Corinth, Pergamus,</hi> and <hi>Thyatira. Platform of diſcipline from New England, chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Yea if all the members of the Church ſhould make but an hypocritical ignorant and verbal profeſſion of Chriſt and faith in him, yet I will not deny but ſuch a ſociety may have the name of a Church; and thus far the nature of it, that the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof are not null. Mr. <hi>Cotton holineſs of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>But there are many precious promiſes made to, and many glorious things ſpoke of the Church of Chriſt, and can they be truely applied to ſuch a Church as this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Look what promiſes are made to the inviſible Church,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> they are for their ſakes offered to all the members of the viſible, whereof the lively are the chief. Mr. <hi>Cotton of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant baptiſme, p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is one thing to propheſie of the tranſcendent glorious happineſs of an exact pure Church in ſome age of it; another to command and foretell the perpetual continuance of it in ſuch a degree of purity. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant bapt. p.</hi> 134. <hi>l.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115279:16"/>Queſt. 4. <hi>But were it not better therefore to gather the Saints, thoſe that are really gracious and holy into bodies by themſelves ſeparate from the reſt that are corrupt members?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This were upon the point to caſt them upon ſuppoſal that theſe corrupt members be ſuch as receive her memberſhip in their infancy out of the Church,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and the Lord hath allowed but two cauſes for the caſting off any perſon out of the Church; firſt, obſtinacy perſiſted in after the admonition fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an offence firſt private, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. Secondly, breaking ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into ſome heinous crime againſt the light of nature, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton holineſs of Church-members, p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But if ſuch members as theſe are, be not to be caſt out, nor withdrawn from, what is to be done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as are born of Chriſtian parents, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in their infancy into the fellowſhip of the Church,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> are ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated members of the ſame Church, though deſtitute of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual grace, untill they juſtly deprive themſelves of the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that fellowſhip, for even of ſuch is the Kingdom of God, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.14. Mr. <hi>Cotton holineſs of Church-members, pag.</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such members of the Church as were born in the ſame, and received their memberſhip in their infancy by vertue of the covenant of their parents, when growing to years of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they deſire to be made partakers of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, unto which, becauſe holy things are not to be given to the unworthy, therefore it is requiſite that theſe as well as others ſhould come to their tryal and examination, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their faith and repentance by an open profeſſion thereof, before they be received to the Lords Supper, or otherwiſe not to be admitted thereto. <hi>Platform of diſcipline from New England, chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet theſe Church members that were ſo born, or received in their child-hood before they are capable of being made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of full communion, have many priviledges which others, not Church-members, have not, they are in covenant with God, have the ſeal thereof upon them, to wit, baptiſme; and ſo if not regenerate, are in a more hopeful way of attaining regenerating grace, and all the ſpiritual bleſſings both of the covenant and ſeal, they are alſo under Church-watch, and ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115279:17"/>conſequently ſubject to the reprehenſions, admonitions, and cenſures thereof for their healing and amendment as need ſhall require. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Infants though born in the Church, yet if when they grow up to years, they ſhall degeenrate into a prophane or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous courſe, they ſhall not be tolerated to abide in the Church; yea if they ſhall not take hold of the covenant of their fathers, but content themſelves in an ignorant civil worldly courſe of life, they ſhall not be allowed to enter into the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the ſincere members of the Church at the Lords Table. Mr. <hi>Cotton of infant baptiſm, pag.</hi> 134. <hi>line</hi> 12. <hi>And this he ſpeaks of as the perfection of the New Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of Church-ſtate, now to draw ſome brief poſitions and inferences from theſe particulars.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The faithful Congregations of <hi>England</hi> are true Churches of Chriſt. <hi>See chap.</hi> 3. <hi>anſwer to the firſt queſtion.</hi> Therefore not to be departed from, nor their communion to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipiſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where Word and Sacraments are duly adminiſtred, there is a faithful Congregation a true Church. <hi>See Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer the firſt.</hi> Therefore ſuch a Congregation may challenge from every member of it, what ever duty is owing to any Church of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The eſſence of a true Church is preſerved though there be found in it ſome hypocries and ſome notoriouſly ſcandalous both in judgement and practice. <hi>See chapter</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 2. <hi>anſw.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Though all the members of a particular Church ſhould make but an ignorant hypocritical verbal profeſſion of Chriſt and faith in him, yet there remains not onely the name, but the nature of a Church; ſo far that the actions thereof are not null. <hi>See chap.</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 2. <hi>anſw.</hi> 5. Therefore quere whether there be any Congregation in <hi>England,</hi> ſo ignorant or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as not to be capable of the name and nature of a Church according to this poſition.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Promiſes made to the viſible Church, are made to it for the ſake of the elect that are therein. <hi>See chap.</hi> 3. <hi>anſw.</hi> 11. <hi>queſt.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115279:18"/>6. God allows none tote caſt out of his Church, but for obſtinacy and heinous crimes againſt the light of nature. <hi>See chap.</hi> 3. <hi>anſwer to queſtion</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Such as were baptized in their infancy, as they are not to be received to full communion till they make profeſſion of faith and repentance, ſo neither are they to be rejected, but ſuffered, to enjoy many priviledges in the Church; as Church-watch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their healing and amendment, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 5. Therefore the more injurious they who caſt off ſome hundreds of baptized ones in their congregtions, and ſurfer neither them nor their children to enjoy any more Church-privileges than meer Turkes or Heathens.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Church-officers and their Ordination.</head>
               <p>Queſtion. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat need is there of Officers in the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though Officers be not neceſſary to the ſimple, being of Churches when they be called,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E.</note> yet ordinarily to their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling they are, and to their well-being; and therefore the Lord Jeſus out of his tender compaſſion hath appointed and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed officers, which he would not have done, if they had not been uſeful and needful for the Church. <hi>Platform of diſcipline from New England, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>What officers then hath Christ appointed and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe officers were either extraordinary, or ordinary; extraordinary, as Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary as Elders and Deacons. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>How many ſorts of Elders hath Chriſt appointed in his Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of Elders (who are alſo in Scripture called Biſhops) there are two ſorts;<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E.</note> ſome attend chiefly to the Miniſtry of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115279:18"/>Word, as the Paſtors and Teachers, others attend eſpecially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rule, who are therefore called ruling-Elders. <hi>Platform of diſcipline Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>Have the Paſtor and Teacher a like power in the Miniſtry of the Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are alike charged with the preaching of the Word,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E.</note> and the application thereof, and either of them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the ſeals of the covenant unto the diſpenſation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are alike called, as alſo to execute the cenſures, being a kind of application of the Word. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Is there any ſuch thing as an outward call neceſſary to the conſtituting of a Paſtor or Teacher?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is a ſtanding and a ſtaple rule, <hi>No man taketh this honour to himſelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but he that is called, is Aaron,</hi> Heb. 5.9. Mr. <hi>Hookers Surney of diſcipline, part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 42. <hi>line</hi> 33.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Without this call none can warrantably do any act that belongs to any officer. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 45. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Without this whatever is done in that behalf is void and of none effect. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>May none then preach the Word and adminiſter the Sacraments in the Church, but the Paſtor or Teachers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are far from allowing that ſacrilegious uſurpation of the Miniſters office which we hear of, (to our grief) to be practiſed in ſome places, that private Chriſtians ordinarily take upon them to preach the Goſpel publickly, and to miniſter the Sacraments. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys. pag.</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 33. It is a frenzy of the Anabaptiſts that begins to labour with the loathſomneſſe of it ſelf, that any Chriſtian gifted, who can teach or miniſter a word of inſtruction to win a Diſciple after him, that he in a corner may baptize him alſo whom he hath won to his opinion. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> their madneſſe is made appear to all who are not willing to ſhut their eyes againſt the Sunne when it ſhines in its beauty.</p>
               <p>For if the Lord Chriſt in his infinite wiſdome and Kingly care, conceived it neceſſary for the honour of the place, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the work of the Deacon to appoint choice men, and ſolemn ordination to authorize them to the work, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called and fitted to the work, might be accepted therein of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115279:18"/>the people, and bleſſed of him who did appoint them to the employment. In reaſon, what greater need is there that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are peculiarly gifted, and furniſhed with grace and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitity, ſhould be called to this work of preaching and diſpenſing theſe holy myſteries, a ſervice above all other of greateſt weight and worth.</p>
               <p>Adde hereunto that the Apoſtle, as by a flaming Sword doth ſtop the way to all pretenders, and therefore layes in this prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition. <hi>No man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God,</hi> as <hi>Aaron,</hi> he muſt have a ſpecial call from God, who muſt dare to meddle with a ſervice which is of ſuch peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar eminence in the houſe of God; yea, the Lord himſelf doth appropriate this, and that to ſome perſons whom he puts in place. <hi>He gave ſome to be Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> Epheſ. 4.11. <hi>Are all Apoſtles? are all Governours? are all Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers?</hi> 1 Cor. 12.29. This would bring confuſion, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the whole. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <hi>line</hi> 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 42. <hi>line</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>But doth not the Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.31. <hi>ſay,</hi> you may all propheſie one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That place in the <hi>Corniths</hi> doth not ſpeak of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary private members,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> but of men furniſhed with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts, the Members of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> (as of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Churches in the primitive times) <hi>were enriched with all knowledge, and in all utterance,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.5. and the ſame perſons which had the gift of propheſie in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> had alſo the gift of tongues, which put upon the Apoſtle a neceſſity to take them off from their frequent ſpeaking with tongues, by preferring propheſie before it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. from <hi>ver.</hi> 2. to 24. ſo that though all they might propheſie having extraordinary gifts for it, yet the like liberty is not allowed to them that want the like gifts.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> none beſides the Prieſts and the Levites did ordinarily propheſie, either in the Temple, or in the Synagogues, unleſſe they were either furniſhed with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts of Propheſſie, as the Prophets of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or were ſet apart, and train'd up to prepare for ſuch a calling as the ſons of the Prophets. When <hi>Amos</hi> was forbidden by the high
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115279:19"/>Prieſt of <hi>Bethel</hi> to propheſie at <hi>Bethel, Amos</hi> doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor plead the liberty of an Iſraelite to propheſie in the holy Aſſemblies, but alledgeth only his extraordinary calling, <hi>Amos</hi> 7.14,15. It appears alſo that the ſons of the Prophets, that is, that men ſet apart and train'd up to prepare for that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, were allowed the like liberty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But neither the ſons of the Prophets, nor the Prophets themſelves were wont to offer ſacrifices in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (except <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> by ſpecial direction) nor did the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets in <hi>Corinth</hi> take upon them to adminiſter the Sacraments. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. page</hi> 20. <hi>line</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>But if the Prophets in the Church of</hi> Corinth <hi>had been ended with extraordinary gifts of Propheſie, they had not been ſubject to the judgment of the Prophets, which theſe are directed to be,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It follows not; for the people of God were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine all Propheſies by the Law and Teſtimony,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them but according to that rule, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. Yea, and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf referred all his doctrine to the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. And the <hi>Bareans</hi> are commended for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine according to the Scripture. <hi>Idem. pag.</hi> 21. <hi>line</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>But though every private Chriſtian may not, yet may not the Magiſtrate either inferiour or ſupreme, preach and adminiſter the Sacraments? hath not he a power Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As it is unlawful for Church-Officers to meddle with the Sword of the Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E.</note> ſo it is unlawful for the Magiſtrate to meddle with the work proper to Church-Officers; the acts of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David</hi> who were not only Princes, but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, were extraordinary, therefore not imitable. Againſt ſuch uſurpation the Lord witneſſed, by ſmiting <hi>Uzziah</hi> with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie for preſuming to offer incenſe. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from New Engl. chap.</hi> 17. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imberare,</hi> (that is to rule) and <hi>praedicare,</hi> (that is to preach) are not compatible, (that is, cannot agree to one and the ſame perſon) hath been a ruled caſe, admitting no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in an ordinary way. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 13. <hi>line</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115279:19"/>Queſt. 8. <hi>You we even now mentioning Ordination, are then theſe Officers which Christ hath appointed in his Church, to be ordained to their Office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Church-Officers are not only to be choſen by the Church,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> but alſo to be ordained by impoſition of hands and prayer, with which, at the Ordination of Elders, faſting alſo is to be joyned. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from New England. chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>But is not Election alone enough without Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No; for as Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> ſaith, Election gives <hi>jus ad rem;</hi> Ordination gives <hi>jus in re.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipilne. part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 40. <hi>line penult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>Is then the right of Ordination im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which is a fundamental point of Religion,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> that hath divine inſtitution, and ſo becomes immutable, unleſſe Chriſt himſelf repeal it. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>But Ordination is a fundamental point of Religion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>Laying on of hands,</hi> being by a Metonymie of the adjunct, put for Ordination. Mr. <hi>Hooker. part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>To whom then doth the power of ordaining Officers. in the Church of Chriſt belong?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Ordination is an act of rule,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and pertains to the Presbyters. Mr. <hi>Cotton way. pag.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Churches are rightly conſtituted and complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the orders and officers of Chriſt, the right of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation belongs to the teaching Elders, the act appertains to the Presbytery conſtituted of teaching and ruling Elders. Mr. <hi>Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>But what if there be no Elders in the Church, who ſhall ordain the Officers then?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In ſuch Churches where there are no Elders, and the Church ſo deſire,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> we ſee not why impoſition of hands may not be performed by the Elders of other Churches. <hi>Platforme of Diſc. from N. E. chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 13. <hi>Are the Word and Sacraments to be diſpenſed by the Miniſters thereof, only in publick or in private alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115279:20"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They muſt be diſpenſed publickly in the preſence,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> and with the concurrence of the Church ſolemnly aſſembled. It is not in the power of the Church to confine preaching to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; <hi>for wiſdome cryeth openly in the ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ets,</hi> Prov. 8.2, 3. And of old, the Church of the Jewes erected Synagogues in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City, beſides the Temple at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for the hearing and preaching of the Word. And the Apoſtle, as he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res the Supper of the Lord to their ordinary ſupper; ſo he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth manifeſtly the Church or Congregation to the private houſe, and declareth that the Lords Supper ſhould be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Congregation, as the banquet ſhould be kept in their private houſe. Yea, the ſcope and nature of the Ordinance calls for ſuch an adminiſtration, for ſince the Sacraments are badges to ſhew our ſeparation from all other profane ſocieties, and to ſignifie our communion one with another, viſibly in the profeſſion and confeſſion of the faith, as our ſpiritual union and communion with Chriſt our head myiſtcally; therefore the adminiſtration of them ſhould be ſuch as ſhould ſuit the nature of the Ordinances, and ſerve the end of it. And therefore it is that in times of perſecution when the Church dares not, nor is meet ſhe ſhould ſhew her ſelf to the enemy; yet not then is the Word nor Sacraments privately preached nor adminiſtred neither, yet ought to be; for though they be done in the houſe of a private man, yet becauſe they are and ought to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in the preſence of the Congregation, there is neither private preaching, nor private celebrating of the Sacrament. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <hi>line</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>To whom are the Paſtors and Teachers of the Church to diſpenſe the Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A perſon hath his firſt right to a Sacrament, becauſe he hath an intereſt in the Covenant of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> of which it is a ſeal; but he muſt come to it in a right order of Chriſt; that is, the party muſt be a Member of a viſible Congregation, becauſe the ſeals can there only be rightly and orderly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred. I ſay it is ſufficient the party be a member of a viſible Congregation, not this or that particular. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Yet it is requisite that ſuch members of a particular Church as were baptized and received their memberſhip in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115279:20"/>ſhould come to their tryal and examination, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt their faith and repentance by an open profeſſion thereof, before they come to the Lords Supper, or elſe not be admitted thereunto. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from New England. chap.</hi> 12 <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>How is this tryal and examination to be made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In caſe any through exceſſive fear or other infirmity,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> be unable to make the relation of their ſpiritual eſtate in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, it is ſufficient that the Elders having received private ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, make relation thereof in publick, before the Church, they teſtifying their aſſent thereunto; this being the way that tendeth moſt to edification. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline. chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>And this is neceſſary for ſome, and warrantable for all, (women) it is moſt without exception to receive all, (wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men after the ſame manner) Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 37.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> 16. <hi>But may thoſe that are members of one Church partake of the Sacraments in another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The members of one Church occaſionally coming to another,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> we willingly admit them to partake with us at the Lords Table, it being the ſeal of our communion, not only with Chriſt, nor only with the members of our own Church, but with all the Churches of the Saints. <hi>Platform of Diſcipline. chap.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 17. <hi>But this priviledge is reſtrained only to members of gathered Churches, is it not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The members that come commended from the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Congregations in <hi>England</hi> to ours here,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that it doth appear to the judgment of the Church whence they come, that they are by them approved, and not ſcandalous, they ought to be received into Church communion with us, as members of other Churches in <hi>New Engl.</hi> in like caſes ſo commended and approved. <hi>Hookers Survey. Preface. A.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 18. <hi>Are the adminiſtrations of men outwardly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the work of the Miniſtry, valid though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelves be deſtitute of inward ſanctity and ſaving grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115279:21"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who ever in a regular way hath received this outward call,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> is a compleat and true officer, and may act any part of his office, though not inwardly graced, and fitted worthily for ſuch a place and work by God. The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Chaire, had this outward call to that office, therefore they muſt be heard by Gods own charge, though they were moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy men, had neither ſufficiency of parts to do the work of the place, nor yet ſincerity of heart and life to endeavour, much leſſe to diſcharge the weight of the ſervices which ſhould be done by them, being blinde guides, painted ſepulchres, groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hypocritical, and ſcandalouſly vile in their general courſe, corrupting the Law by their falſe and unlearned gloſſes, and perverting the ſimple by their lewd carriages, polluting all Gods Ordinances by their corrupt handling, and adminiſtration thereof. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 45. <hi>line</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 19. <hi>Is the office of the ruling Elder diſtinct from the Paſtour and Teacher?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ruling Elders office is diſtinct from the office of the Paſtour and Teacher.<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> 
                  <hi>Platform of Diſcipline from N. E. chap.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 20. <hi>Why is this officer called a ruling Elder?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ruling Elders are not ſo called to exclude the Paſtors and Teachers from ruling;<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> but becauſe ruling and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning is common to theſe with the other, whereas attending to teach and preach the Word is peculiar to the former. <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of Diſc. chap.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 21. <hi>How do you prove that there is ſuch an Office as a ruling Elder appointed by Chriſt in the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That there is ſuch an office and officer appointed by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> as the Scriptures are plain to him whoſe ſpirit and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion is not pre-poſſeſſ't and fore-ſtalled with prejudice, ſo this hath been maintained by many of Chriſts worthies of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and of later times.</p>
               <p>So that we have no controverſie here but with hierarchical perſons, the force of whoſe argument lies eſpecially in a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevant and a priſon, armed with authority of a high Commiſſion. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115279:21"/>Queſt. 22. <hi>But what Scripture have you to bottome this office upon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt argument we have from <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7.<note place="margin">Mr.
<hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He that ruleth with diligence.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 28.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way of the Churches, pag.</hi> 13. <hi>line</hi> 31.</p>
               <p>The ſecond argument is taken from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>God hath ſet in his Church governments.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 10. <hi>line</hi> 15. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way of the Churches. page</hi> 15. <hi>line</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>A third argument is taken from that famous place which is full to the purpoſe; <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey. part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 11. <hi>line</hi> 25. Mr. <hi>Cottons way. page</hi> 19. <hi>line</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 23. <hi>What is the work of the ruling Elder?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ruling Elders work is to joyn with the Paſtour and Teacher in thoſe acts of ſpiritual rule which are diſtinct from the Miniſtery of the Word and Sacraments committed to them,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> of which ſort are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To open and ſhut the doors of Gods houſe by admiſſion of members, ordination of officers, excommunication of offenders, reſtoring of penitents.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To call the Church together when there is occaſion, and ſeaſonably to diſmiſſe them again.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To prepare matters in private, that in publick they may be carried on with leſſe trouble and more ſpeedy diſpatch.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To moderate the carriage of all matters in the Church aſſembled, to propound matters to the Church, to order the ſeaſon of ſpeech and ſilence, to pronounce ſentence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the minde of Chriſt with the conſent of the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To be guides and leaders to the Church in all matters what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever pertaining to Church-adminiſtrations and actions.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To ſee that none in the Church live inordinately, and out of rank and place, without a calling, or idly in their calling.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To prevent and heal ſuch offences in life or doctrine which might corrupt the Church.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To feed the flock of God with a word of admonition.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115279:22"/>9. And as they ſhall be ſent for to viſit and pray over their ſick brethren.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And at other times as opportunity ſhall ſerve thereunto. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from New<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> England. chap.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>line</hi> 20. <hi>Idem. of the Keys. pag.</hi> 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 16.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And by the ſame parity of reaſon if any want comfort, ſinking under diſcouragements and ſadneſſe of ſpirit, or through ignorance are not able to underſtand the things delivered, they may call for the help of the Elder in private, that they may be informed and comforted by him. And hence it follows,</p>
               <p n="12">12. That he hath power to enquire into the condition, and take account of the ſpecial ſtate of ſuch of the members; for elſe how ſhould he be able to adminiſter ſeaſonable and ſutable ſupport? Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 17. <hi>line</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>And that theſe eſpecially the laſt mentioned, are works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Ruling Elder, the nature of the thing would ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perſwade a mans reaſon to yield thereunto; for how une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and unreaſonable would it ſeem to a man acquainted with the weight and work of the Miniſtery, that when the Paſtor or Teacher ſhould be attending upon reading and ſearching the ſenſe and minde of God in his Word, and the myſteries of God therein, (who is ſufficient for theſe things) that they ſhould be then taken off their ſtudies, and forced to attend upon mens ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial weakneſſes and wants in private, when they ſhould prepare for the publick diſpenſations, ſo that the one muſt of neceſſity be neglected, or they diſtracted in both. Whereas this appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Saviour provides for both without prejudice or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage to either. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey. part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 18. <hi>line</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 24. <hi>You have ſhewn fully what is the work of the Ruling Elders; but I pray tell me what is that power they are cloathed with in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe acts of theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Negatively it is not. 1. Any Lordly pompous power.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shepherds.</hi>
                  </note> 2. It is not any Antichriſtian unlimited power. Nor. 3. Is it and Magiſterial power. Mr. <hi>Shepherds wholeſome caveat for a time of liberty. pag.</hi> 97.98, 99.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115279:22"/>But poſitively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They have power given them of ruling and governing from Chriſt by the people; hence they are called Rulers, and have a ſtrict charge and command from the Lord to rule. <hi>Idem. page</hi> 99.</p>
               <p>Hence thoſe caſt off the Lords government over then who will have no Rulers nor Governours in the Church, but leave all to themſelves and their liberty, and ſo by this means they are not only ſingle members or officers, but Paſtor, Teacher and Elder, and all. This generation of men, ſons of <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> are riſen up in theſe later times, eſpecially among Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts and rigid Separatiſts, whoſe condemnation ſleeps not, Satan carrying them to extreams, and pride lifting them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove themſelves, above men, above Officers, above Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, above God. <hi>Idem. page</hi> 100. <hi>line</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This power which the Ruling-Elder hath, is more than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one member hath which is not an Officer. It would be a moſt ſimple ridiculous thing if there ſhould be Election, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, many prayers, much tryal of men to rule and guide and govern, ſeparation from the reſt, and yet to have no more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than any other private member; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſubmit to them that are over you,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.12. <hi>Obey them that rule over you,</hi> Heb. 13.17. Maſter <hi>Shepherds wholſome caveat, &amp;c. page</hi> 100. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>Hence thoſe that do acknowledge Gevernours in the Church for names ſake, but they are ſuch as have no more power than a private brother: They are to watch, ſay they, ſo are private members, to admoniſh, ſo is every private member, &amp;c. theſe allow the name, but deny the thing. <hi>Idem. page</hi> 101. <hi>line</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo when men ſhall cry for liberty to ſpeak, an Elder forbids it; what may not the Church have liberty? yes true, but you are not the Church. An Elder reproves, they will reprove again; what ſhall not the Church have liberty? An Elder gives reaſons ſtrong and unanſwerable for ſomething to be done, a young fellow ſteps up and ſaith without ground or ſhew of it, that is your light, and mine is otherwiſe; what may not the Church have liberty? yes, but you are not the Church. This is very ſad, and hath been a root of greateſt ſcandal that ever Gods wayes had. <hi>Idem. page</hi> 102. <hi>line</hi> 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115279:23"/>3. In the execution of their office according to Chriſt, they are over the whole Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. Obey them that rule you; he ſpeaks to the whole Church. Mr. <hi>Shepherds wholeſome cave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. pag.</hi> 102. <hi>line</hi> 26. Their power rightly executed is the power of Chriſt. Hence refuſe it, you refuſe to be ſubject to him, if men will not be ruled by ordinances, but will rule ordinances, they go about to rule Chriſt. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 104. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They have power to overſee when they ſee cauſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. and to enquire into the ſtate of the flock, to know their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual condition. Mr. <hi>Shepherd pag.</hi> 105. <hi>line</hi> 20. Hence men caſt off the government of Chriſt when they will not have their ſpiritual condition ſearched into; the Elders foot is now too great for his ſhoe. I am to give an account to God, ſo are they alſo of theirs. Now thou canſt not give it if thou enquireſt not how thy condition ſtands, neither can they with comfort, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou telleſt them how it ſtands with thee. <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 106. <hi>l.</hi> 3. The Miniſters charge is to caſt the ſeed, the Elders duty is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after the fruit in the husbandry of Chriſt; but you can quarrel and ſnap at the Elders when they come to enquire of your condition; and why do you enquire? you take too much upon you. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They have power to guide counſel, and warn the Church, at leaſt in all weighty affairs which may concern them and their common good, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Malac.</hi> 2.7. Mr. <hi>Shepherd pag.</hi> 106. Hence for men in matters of great and weighty affairs which concern the good of the whole Church, nay all Churches, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to enquire at <hi>Abel,</hi> is a caſting off the Lord: as in election of Officers in the Church, or Magiſtrates in the Commonwealth. Hence to receive any opinion different from all the Elders in the Church, and never ſo much as ſpeak, much leſs come to a ſad debate about it, is to caſt off this yoak: Hence to propoſe a doubtful queſtion to the Church which may trouble or bring an offenders ſin to the Church without councel of the Elders; hence when men will not take warning from the Elders of evil to come, it is a caſting off the Lords yoke, <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They have power of publike reproof of any member of the Church, in caſe of plain, open, and publike offences, others without leave cannot nor ought not. Reproofs are part of the power peculiar to the Governors in any ſociety where Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115279:23"/>are preſent and at hand. In a family no wiſe man will ſuffer brawles among children and ſervants, but ſaith he, Tell me, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p>Now this is ſad when a man cannot bear reproof of others, nor bear reproofs of Elders, but turns again and will be judge in his own caſe, though never ſo groſs; a ſign of an extream froward high ſpirit. Mr. <hi>Shepherd pag.</hi> 108.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They are to feed in power, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies, every one in their places. Hence when men deſpiſe their food, and they are poor things they ſpeak, and they can ſee no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in them (and that after ſtudy, prayers and tears) and ſo caſt it by, that is to caſt off the Lord; when men grow glutted and full, that they eat not a bit, theſe things call for chains. Mr. <hi>Shepherd, pag.</hi> 109.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 25. <hi>But why are you thus large in ſetting out the work and power of the ruling elder?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe the Apoſtle in many of his Epiſtles lays a ſpecial charge upon the people <hi>to have a care of the Officers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shepherd.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and obey them,</hi> Heb. 13.7, 17. It is twice repeated; firſt leaſt officers be ſadded in their work that is heavy. Secondly, leaſt it be unprofitable for you; you think to get this and that good by it, but it will be nothing in the concluſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe we lye under the ſlander of many, and that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if Elders in Churches were but onely ciphers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe people begin to run into extreams, Elders taking all to themſelves, and people all to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe if here be not attendance, you will quickly ſee the miſerable ruine and fall of Churches more ſad than the burning of <hi>Solomons</hi> temple. It is obſerved of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> that when he ſtretched out his hand againſt the Lords Prophet it was withered, but not when he ſacrificed; for the Lord will not bear here; they may be deſpiſed and you may think your ſelves Kings without them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. and men will ſay ſo, they may rule as they will, but you will do as you liſt, but the Lord will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked for this. Mr. <hi>Shepherd his wholeſome caveat for a time of liberty, pag.</hi> 109, 110.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 26. <hi>But ſeeing there is ſuch plain ground in Scripture for the office of the ruling Elder, and ſeeing it is ſo uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the Church, what is the reaſon there is ſo much gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying and oppoſing this office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115279:24"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> It is no wonder to ſee the contention grow ſo hot touching a ruling Elder, becauſe if he be confined within his compaſs, the wings of the Pope and Prelate will be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly clipped, arid their power empeached. Mr. <hi>Hookers Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of diſcipline, part</hi> 2 <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>line</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Satans ſubtilty lies here, Diſgrace the Elder ſaith one, divide them ſaith another, pull them down ſaith a third, that there may be no King in Iſrael, no nor in Sion, that we may do what is right in our own eyes. Mr. <hi>Shepherds wholeſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat, pag.</hi> 110. <hi>line</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 27. <hi>What ſay you of the other Officers called Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> All men do acknowledge them both to be inſtituted by Chriſt in the Scriptures, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and continued in the Church throughout all ages. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way, pag.</hi> 38. <hi>line</hi> 7. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, part</hi> 2. 32. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 28. <hi>VVhat is the Deacons office?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> His Office is to attend tables, <hi>i. e.</hi> to lay out the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury and revenue of the Church as may be behoveful. 1. For to provide elements for the Lords table when that ſhould be attended. 2. For the table of the poor for all their wants that they may be ſupplied (whether of their own bodie or ſtrangers.) Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way, pag.</hi> 38. <hi>line</hi> 26.3. For the table of the Miniſter, whatever proviſion the Church ſhall put into their hands to be adminiſtred to them according to that debt which the Church owes them in way of wages. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 38. <hi>line</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 29. <hi>Is then the Miniſters maintenance and the Poors to come all out of one ſtock or common treaſury?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> 1. No: for firſt all are not bound to pay it to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of the poor, but all are bound to pay to the maintenance of the Miniſter, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. People are bound to make their teachers partakers of all their good things: not ſo the poor.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This coupling of the poor and Miniſters in one common treaſury, confounds the works of Juſtice and Mercy. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline. part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 30. <hi>line</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 30. <hi>VVhat was the chief aim of our Saviour in ſetting theſe officers in his Church?.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115279:24"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The chief aim of our Saviour (under the glory of his name) was to provide for the eſpecial good of his elect; yet becauſe thoſe his elect were mingled here with the wicked in the world; nay, many an elect child proceeds of a reprobate parent, and becauſe it is impoſſible for the eye of man to ſearch into heart ſecrets and inward ſincerity which is covered there, but muſt judge of men, and diſpenſe Ordinances unto men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the limits and laws of rational charity; therefore it is that our Saviour hath beſtowed theſe Offices as a royall gift upon the viſible Church over whom he is a head Political by outward guidance and government, as well as a head myſtical by his ſpecial and ſpiritual conveyance of his grace. Mr. <hi>Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Survey of diſcipline, part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 29.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of Church Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now to draw ſome poſitions out of theſe particulars with inferences thereupon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Officers are ordinarily neceſſary to the calling of a Church, and to the well-being of it, when called, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>queſt.</hi> 1. <hi>anſw.</hi> Therefore the way of gathering or calling Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as it is uſed here in <hi>England,</hi> is prepoſterous where the Church calls and conſtitutes it ſelf firſt, and then afterwards conſtitutes an Officer or Officers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. None can warrantably do any act that belongs to an office without a call to that office; and if he do, it is void and of none effect. Yea, it is a ſacrilegious uſurpation, an Anabaptiſtical frenzy for private Chriſtians to take upon them ordinarily to preach the Goſpel publikely, <hi>&amp;c. Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>queſt.</hi> 4, 5. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the brethren of the Church-way conſider their practice of ſending out their private brethren and members to preach ordinarily in the Country Pariſhes, how warrantable it is: and if every act of an office done without a Call to the office, be void and null, whether ſuch publike preaching of private Chriſtians, be not a taking Gods name in vain, a mocking of God and the ſouls of his people, and ſacriledge inſtead of ſacrifice.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115279:25"/>3. That famous text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. gives no countenance at all to preaching of private men, and ſuch as are not in office. <hi>to queſt.</hi> 5. <hi>Obj.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Chriſt hath appointed in his Church not one but many Officers, Paſtors, Teachers, Rulers, and Deacons, and none of theſe ſuperfluous, but all uſeful and needful, all given in wiſdom and compaſſion to his Church. <hi>queſt.</hi> 1, 2. 3. Therefore how thoſe Churches can be ſaid to come neereſt the rule, and walk cloſeſt to the rule, who either have no officers at all, as the Church of H. and the Church of N. or elſe content themſelves with one officer, a Paſtor, having neither Teacher, Ruler, nor Deacon, as moſt of the gathered Churches in <hi>England;</hi> is this to walk according to rule? is not this either to ſlight the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of Chriſt in giving theſe officers, or to contradict the wiſdom of Chriſt, and proclaim thoſe offices needleſs and uſeleſs, which Chriſt judged needful and uſeful, and therefore appointed in his Church?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ordination is a fundamental in Church diſcipline, and gives the officer right in his office, <hi>jus in re. See queſt.</hi> 9, 10. Therefore ordination is more than election, which onely gives <hi>jus ad rem;</hi> And quaere how many Miniſters of our gathered Churches can have a full right and authority to adminiſter all ordinances, having onely election of the people, which gives but <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> and not ordination which give <hi>jus in re.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Ordination is an act of rule, and pertaines to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tersy or Presbytery <hi>Que.</hi> 11. Therefore not to the fraternity or body of the people.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Word and Sacraments are to be diſpenſed in publike.</p>
                  <p>Queſt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Therefore why do many of the Church-way ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently baptize children in private?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raments are badges to ſhew our ſeparation from all profane Societies, and to ſignifie our communion one with another in the profeſſion and confeſſion of the faith, as our ſpiritual union and communion with Chriſt our head myſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>See qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt.</hi> 13. <hi>anſw.</hi> Therefore the Sacraments are notes of the true Church, as the Proteſtant writers have alwayes main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt the Papiſts.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. A perſon hath his firſt right to the Sacrament, becauſe he hath an intereſt in the covenant of the Goſpel, of which it is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115279:25"/>a ſeal. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 14. Therefore the Church covenant, as they call it, gives not a man his firſt right to the Sacrament, for that is not the covenant of the Goſpel, nor is the Sacrament a ſeal of that.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. For the receiving of the Sacrament in a right order of Chriſt, it is ſufficient that the party be a member of a viſible Congregation, not this or that particular. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 14. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether the Congregation be conſtituted after this or that form, by expreſs covenant or not, whether it be an Independent Congregation or a Claſſical Congregation, it is all one if a man be a member of a viſible Congregation, he comes in a right order of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. It is requiſite that thoſe who were baptized and received their member-ſhip in their infancy, ſhould come to their tryal and examination, before they be admitted to the Supper; and this examination may be made by the Elders, yea in ſome caſes it is neceſſary it ſhould be ſo; and for all women it is moſt warrantable and moſt without exception. Therefore ſuch exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in Presbyterian Churches, is not ſinful and unlawful, nor deſerves ſo much ignominy and ſcorn, as ſome have caſt upon it.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The Sacraments are ſeals not onely of our communion with Chriſt, and with the members of our own Church, but with all the Churches of the Saints. <hi>See quest.</hi> 16. Therefore they who will partake with none but the members of their own Church, or a Church of the like conſtitution, nor ſuffer their members to partake in none but their own Churches, are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the greateſt breach of Chriſtian love that can be, unſaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unchurching all the Churches that Chriſt hath upon the earth but themſelves, and with a kinde of Papal pride, judging and (as much as in them is) excommunicating all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, contrary to their own principles that ſay, No one Church hath power over another.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. The wickedneſs of a Miniſter does no wayes make void the acts of his Miniſtry, nor give the people a diſpenſation to contemn it. <hi>See queſt.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The ruling Elders office is ſo clearly and fully grounded in Scripture, as none can controvert it, but he whoſe ſpirit and apprehenſion is prepoſſeſt and foreſtalled with prejudice. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 21.22.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115279:26"/>15. The power and work of the ruling Elder, is very great, and his office very needful in the Church. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 23, 24. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that will have none of theſe ruling Elders over them, but leave all to themſelves and their liberty, and by this means are not onely ſingle members or officers, but Paſtors and Teachers and Elders and all; This generation of men caſt off the Lords government, are ſons of <hi>Korah,</hi> whoſe condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſleeps not, <hi>&amp;c. Queſt.</hi> 24. <hi>anſw.</hi> 1. Quaere, whether ſome others be not guilty of this as well as Anabaptiſts, Familiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. If the ruling Elder be confined within his compaſs, the wings of the Pope and Biſhop will be clipt, and their power exceedingly impeached. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 25. Therefore there is neither truth or modeſty in them that ſay the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is managed by ruling Elders as well as the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational, is as tyrannical as Prelacy, and as Antichriſtian as Popery.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. It is the divels ſubtilty to diſgrace, divide, pull down the ruling Elder. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 23. Let them therefore conſider whoſe work they do, and what reward (without repentance) they are like to have who drive ſuch a deſign.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Deacons are officers inſtituted by Chriſt, and needful to be continued in the Church. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 26.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The maintenance of Miniſters is an act of juſtice, not mercy; debt, not almes. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 28.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Officers and Ordinances are beſtowed upon the viſible Church, not for their ſake, but for the ſake of the elect that are among them whoſe good (next under his own glory) Chriſt principally intended. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 29. Therefore the viſible Church is not firſt in Chriſts intention. Therefore the viſible Church, eſpecially the Church of a particular Congregation, as ſuch, hath no reaſon to boaſt her ſelf in her priviledges, as the Spouſe, and Lacy, and Queen of Chriſt, ſeeing theſe and all other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges are given her, not for her own ſake, but for the ſake of the elect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115279:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Church Government and Cenſures.</head>
               <p>Queſtion 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHo are the ſeat or ſubject of Church Rule or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Church government or Rule is placed by Chriſt in the officers of the Church,<note place="margin">Platform of diſcipline.</note> who therefore are called Rulers; the holy Ghoſt frequently, yea alwayes when he mentioneth Church Rule and Church Government, aſcribeth it to El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; whereas the worke and duty of people is expreſſed in the phraſe of obeying their Elders, and ſubmitting themſelves to them in the Lord. <hi>Platform of diſcipline from New England, Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>How is Church government to be conſidered?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Church government is to be attended, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the eſſentials or circumſtantials of it, Mr. <hi>Hooker, part.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>What are the eſſentials of Church government?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The eſſentials required to the compleating of Church government, are partly in the perſons that diſpenſe, partly in the Ordinances that are diſpenſed. <hi>Ibid. p. line</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>What is eſſential in the perſons that diſpenſe the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the perſons that diſpenſe, the kinds of officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that work, the nature, bounds and limits of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, all theſe are eſſentials. Mr. <hi>Hooker, ibid. line</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>What are the Ordinances that theſe are to diſperſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Ordinances that theſe are to diſpenſe, are, Preaching, Prayer, Seals, Church cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe all are to be found in the Word, an fetched from the Word, and now under the Goſpel, they are and ought to be the ſame in all places, amongſt all people, at all times in all ſucceeding generations untill the coming of Chriſt. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>May there then be no alteration in theſe things which you call eſſentials?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115279:27"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not left in the power of perſons, Officers, Churches, nor all the States in the world, to add or diminiſh or alter any thing in the leaſt meaſure: But as God did appoint all in the old Teſtament, and thoſe Inſtitutions did endure there ever (as Scripture ſpeaks) untill the coming of Chriſt, when the ſame power which appointed, changed them: So in the new Teſtament where are to expect no alteration, Chriſt the Law-giver he onely appoints; none but he can; and he hath made known his will, that he will not change them. Mr. <hi>Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Survey, part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>What are the circumſtantials of government?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The circumſtantials of diſcipline, as time, place, the carrying on of theſe diſpenſation in civil decencies ſuitable to the quality of the things and conditions of the time, as peace and perſecution; the general rules of theſe are in the Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; but the particular application admits varieties, muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities and alterations according as neceſſities or convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſhall appear by emergent occaſions. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey part</hi> 1 <hi>page</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>You have ſpoken already of moſt of the eſſentials of Church government, namely Officers and Ordinances of worſhip; but what ſay you of Church cenſures? are they neceſſary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The cenſures of the Church are appointed by Chriſt for the preventing, removing, and healing of offences in the Church, for the reclaiming and gaining of offending brethren, for the deterring others from the like offences, for purging out the leaven which may infect the whole lump; for vindicating the honor of Chriſt, and of his Church, and the holy profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Goſpel, and for preventing the wrath of God which may juſtly fall upon the Church, if they ſhould ſuffer his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and the ſeals thereof to be prophaned by notorious and obſtinate offenders. <hi>Platform of diſcipline from New England, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>How many cenſures are there in the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Three; the firſt admonition, the ſecond ſuſpenſion, the third excommunication.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>What is admonition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Admonition is of two ſorts; the firſt more private, when the offended brother admoniſheth the offender of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115279:27"/>according to the rule of Chriſt, between him and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender alone. The ſecond leſſe private, and yet not publike, when he takes one or two with him. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. Mr. <hi>Cottons way pag.</hi> 89.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>But what if the offending party be not gained by either of theſe admonitions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The offended brother tells the Church of it, to wit, in Gods way. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way, pag.</hi> 90. <hi>line</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>What do you mean by telling the Church in Gods way?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The offended brother is by the mouth of the Elders to tell it the Church. <hi>Platform of diſcipline from N. E. chap. ſect.</hi> 2. That is, he telleth the Elders who are the mouth of the Church, that by them it may be preſented before the Church. Mr. <hi>Cottons way, pag.</hi> 90. <hi>line</hi> 13. The matter muſt firſt be brought to the Elders, and by them debated and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Church. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, part</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 36, <hi>l.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 13. <hi>But why muſt the mattor be firſt brought to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and debated by them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For that they are guides and leaders of the Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. the watchmen and overſeers of it; and therefore they muſt know the cauſes and controverſies; to the full in all circumſtances, difficulties, windings and turnings thereof, that they may be able to lead the Congregation in the way of peace and truth, which they cannot do unleſſe they know the way themſelves. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>line</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To them it appertains to judge, whether the things be of weight and worth, and ſo need and require the preſence and aſſiſtance of the body to expreſſe their judgement againſt them, and the party guilty of them or no; for if they be petty buſineſſes, and altogether unfit and unworthy to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Congregation withall, it is in their power to prevent ſuch cauſeleſs and needleſs diſturbance, and therefore to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe any further proceeding therein. Mr. <hi>Hooker, part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>line</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But by this means, if the Elders be corrupt in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or partial in affections, they may ſilence the weighteſt cauſe that can be, and ſo prejudice the innocency of thoſe they are not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115279:28"/>friendly to, and hinder the reformation of thoſe whom in a corrupt and partial way they ſinfully favour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Therefore as it is in their power to ſuppreſſe ſuch pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty occaſions as are not worthy the times, pains, and diſturban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that muſt be ſpent upon them: So yet to prevent injuſtice and partiality in ſuch caſes, the party who takes himſelf wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may complain of the Elders in that behalf; and if the Congregation ſee apparently that they have dealt unjuſtly and partially, it is in their power to rectifie; but if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints prove unjuſt and unreaſonable, be it at the peril of him that complains; for he is to be cenſured ſharply and ſeverely, as out of pride and perverſeneſſe, refuſing to liſten to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable advice and counſel of thoſe who were ſet over him by the Lord; as alſo becauſe he had needleſly diſturbed the peace of the Congregation as much as in him lies. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline, part</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the preparation is to be made by the Elders, becauſe if the body of the people be numerous, they will be unable with any comely conveniency to weigh all the circumſtances and difficulties which will certainly and neceſſarily occur in ſuch agitation, nor can in reaſon beſtow their times and pains upon them, as the intricacy and perplexity of the work will ſometimes require. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>But what is the work, or power of the Members then in order unto cenſures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the Brethren have a power of order, and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to expoſtulate with their Brethren in caſe of private ſcandal, according to the rule, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16. So in caſe of publick ſcandal, the whole Church of Brethren have power and priviledge to joyne with the Elders, in enquiring, hearing, judging of publick ſcandals, ſo as to binde notorious offenders and impenitents under cenſure, and to forgive the repentant: Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys, page</hi> 13. But yet this enquiring and hearing is not to be underſtood as if the complaint were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and <hi>pro primâ inſtantiâ,</hi> to be brought to the Church or Fraternity. No, but it is firſt to be brought to the Elderſhip, prepared and ripened by them, and by them related to the Church, for the Elders, before that have not onely examined
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115279:28"/>the offender and his offence, and the proofs thereof privately; but, do alſo publickly reviſe the heads of all the material paſſages thereof before the Church, and do withall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the counſel and will of God therein, that they may rightly diſcern and approve what cenſure the Lord requireth to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in ſuch a caſe: Mr, <hi>Cotton of the Keys, page</hi> 14. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>But yet after the Elders have thus exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the caſe, and declared their judgement concerning it, the Church have yet a power to judge; have they not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes; but not as an act of rule and authority; for there is a judgment of diſcretion by way of priviledge, as well as of authority, by way of ſentence; that of diſcretion is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the Brethren, as well as that of authority belongs to the Presbytery of the Church. In <hi>England</hi> the Jury by their verdict, as well as the Judge by his ſentence, do both of them judge the ſame Malefactor; yet in the Jury their verdict is but an act of Popular liberty, in the Judge it is an act of his judicial authority. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys, page</hi> 14. <hi>line</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 16. <hi>What is the difference then between the judgment which the Brethren paſſe in the cenſure of Excommunication, and that which the Elders paſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Great is the difference. For though the Jury have given up their judgment and verdict, yet the Malefactor is not thereupon legally condemned, and much leſſe executed, but upon the ſentence of the Judge. In like ſort here, though the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Church do with one accord give up their vote and judgment for the cenſure of an offender, yet he is not thereby cenſured till upon the ſentence of the Presbytery. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Keyes, page</hi> 14. <hi>line</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 17. <hi>Have then the Brethren no power of authority, but only of priviledge and liberty? Is not binding and looſing an act of authority? and power to binde and looſe, given to the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole Church may be ſaid to binde and looſe, in that the Brethren conſent and concur with the Elders both before the cenſure, diſcerning it to be juſt and equal, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring this by lifting up their hands, or by ſilence ; and after the cenſure, in rejecting the offender cenſured from their wonted communion. <hi>Idem. line</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115279:29"/>Queſt. 18. <hi>Whither is this conſent of the Brethren unto the judgement and ſentence of the Elders concerning the Excommunication of a Member an act of authority, or of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The people give conſent in obedience to the will and rule of Chriſt: Hence is that ſpeech of the Apoſtle, <hi>we have in readineſſe to revenge all diſobedience, when your OBE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIENCE &amp; is fullfilled,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.6. The Apoſtles revenge of diſobedience by way of reproof in preaching, doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the peoples obedience, but proceedeth whether the people obey it or no; it was therefore their revenge of diſobedience by way of cenſure in Diſcipline which they had in readineſſe when the obedience of the Church is fulfilled, in diſcerning and approving the equity of the cenſure, which the Apoſtles and Elders have declared to them from the Word. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes, page</hi> 15. <hi>line</hi> 6. And if the people cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Elder of his errour or miſtake in the ſentence, they are bound to joyne their judgment with his in the compleating of the ſentence, without impertinent queſtions, needleſſe ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wilfull and diſorderly gain-ſayings. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, P.</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 42. <hi>line</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 19. <hi>But what if the caſe prove doubtful, and there ariſe a difference between the Elders and the Brethren?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the caſe be doubtful, and the difference grows wide and great, it is then ſeaſonable to crave the counſel and help of neighbouring Churches. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey, part</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 40. <hi>line</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 20. <hi>May not the Brethren proceed to the ſentence of Excommunication without the Elders?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Excommunication is one of the higheſt acts of rule in the Church, and therefore cannot be performed but by ſome Rulers. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes, page</hi> 16. <hi>line</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But the twenty foure Elders, (who repreſent the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Members of the Church, as the foure living creatures do the foure Officers) had all of them Crowns upon their heads, and ſate upon Thrones, which are ſignes of Regal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115279:29"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Crowns and Thrones argue them to be Kings no more than their white garments argue them to be Prieſts, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. but neither Prieſts nor Kings by office, but by liberty to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms like ſpiritual duties by grace, which others do by office and grace both. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes, page</hi> 16. <hi>line</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 21. <hi>What are the things or caſes for which the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Excommunication is to be inflicted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It muſt not be for petty and ſmall aberrations, but for ſuch evils as the mind and conſcience of a man inlightned by the Church of God would condemn in himſelf, or any upon the firſt ſerious conſideration, was his underſtanding left to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of reaſon to act thereby, and not crack-brained and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted with prejudice and ſelfiſhneſſe. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline, part</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 34. <hi>line</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 22. <hi>But tell us ſomewhat more particularly and expreſſely, what is the matter of Excommunication?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such evils as are either heinous or abominable; as fornication, murder, adultery, inceſt, treaſon, or if not ſo groſſe, yet carry the face of evil in their fore-head, upon the firſt ſerious and well-grounded conſideration of reaſon, and have been pertinaciouſly and obſtinately perſiſted in after all means improved for their conviction and reformation. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline, part</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 34. <hi>line</hi> 37.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 23. <hi>You did a little above</hi> (Queſt.8.) <hi>mention ſuſpenſion as a cenſure diſtinct from Excommunication; in what caſes is that practiſed, or uſed in the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In two Caſes. Firſt thus; Members born in the Church, and having received their Memberſhip in their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, being grown to years of diſcretion, muſt come to tryal and examination, and manifeſt their faith and repentance by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſſion thereof before they be received to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or otherwiſe not to be admitted thereunto. <hi>Platform of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline from New Eng. chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7. (ſee before <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 5.) though thy ſuſpenſion be not ſtrictly a cenſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather <hi>actus charitatis,</hi> than <hi>poteſtatis;</hi> and as they call it, <hi>ſuſpenſio per modum cautelae.</hi> Secondly, thus; while the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending brother lyeth under the cenſure of admonition, he ſtands in the judgment of the whole Church as a convinced
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115279:30"/>publick offender; and therefore till he be reconciled to the Church by the penitent and publick acknowledgement of his ſin before them, he doth abſtain from the Lords Table, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the direction of our Saviour who would not have an offender preſent himſelf nor his guift before the Altar, while the guilt of the offence of his brother lay upon him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. Or as the Prieſts in the Law did forbear to <hi>eat of the holy things whileſt they lay in uncleanneſſe,</hi> Lev. 22. 3, 4. Or as one Who lying in his uncleanneſſe, did rather pollute the holy Ordinance of God by partaking of it, than receive any holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from it. Mr. <hi>Cottons way of the Churches, page</hi> 91. <hi>line</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But this ſeems to be but a voluntary act of the offending party; this is not a Church cenſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Church diſcern the offending brother to be willing to hear, but not yet fully convinced of his offence, as in caſe of Herefie, they are to diſpenſe to him a publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, with declaring the offender to be under the publick of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Church, who doth thereby withhold or ſuſpend him from the holy fellowſhip of the Lords Supper till his offence be removed by penitent confeſſion. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. and this is truly and properly <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>spenſio per modum cenſurae.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of Church Government and Cenſures. Now out of theſe particulars draw we theſe poſitions with inferences thereupon.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Church-government or rule is placed by Chriſt in the officers of the Church, who therefore are called Rulers. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 1. Therefore the fraternity are not the ſeat or ſubject of Rule or power.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The eſſentials of Church-government are unalterable: <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 1. Therefore they who believe ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be eſſentials of government, and yet conſtitute none in their Churches, live in a neglect of duty contrary to their judgment and perſwaſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Church Cenſures are Chriſts appointments. <hi>See anſw. to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115279:30"/>queſt.</hi> 7. and cannot be diſpenſed, at leaſt ſome of them without Rulers. <hi>See anſw. to q.</hi> 19. Therefore Churches that have no Rulers, do not nor cannot obſerve all the Ordinances and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinments of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Petty matters and ſmall aberrations, are not to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by excomunication; but ſuch evils as are either heinous and abominable, or at leaſt are ſuch as the minde and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a man inlightned by the truth of God, would condemn in any upon the firſt ſerious conſideration. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 20, 21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Offences are not immediately and at the firſt daſh to be brought to the Church or community, but firſt to the Elders to be conſidered, debated, ripened by them, received as ſerious and weighty, or rejected as ſlight and frivolous. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 11. And therefore that Tell the Church (which is the next immediate ſtep after the firſt and ſecond, brethren and private admonition) it is not Tell the fraternity or community, but Tell the Elders.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The power which the brethren have in cenſures, it is not a power of rule and authority, but a power of liberty; and the judgement they paſſe, it is not a judgement of authority, but a judgement of diſcretion ; they are but as the Jury, the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is as the Judge. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 14, 15, 16.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Church binds and looſes only by conſenting to the judgement and ſentence of the Elders, which conſent of theirs is an act of obedience, and they are bound to yeeld to it, unleſs they can manifeſt that the judgement of the Elderſhip is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and erroneous. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. In doubtful caſes, and in matters of difference, it is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to crave the help and counſel of neighboring Churches, <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 19.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. There are two ſorts of Church-Members, ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat who are admitted to all Ordinances, ſome incompleate who having received their Memberſhip in their infancy, are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from the Lords Table, and other Church-priviledges, till they have paſſed a tryal, and have received approbation of their fitneſs for thoſe enjoyments. An offending brother ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under publike admonition, is ſuſpended from the Lords Table, before he be excommunicated; therefore ſuſpenſion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115279:31"/>is a cenſure diſtinct from Admonition and Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Combination or Conſotiation of Churches into Claſſes or Synods.</head>
               <p>Queſtion 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHether is it lawful for particular Congregations, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Elders and brethren, and walking with a right foot in the truth and peace of the Goſpel, to joyn together in conſoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation on combination of Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the Church of a particular Congregation, conſiſting of Elders and Brethren,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be the firſt ſubject of all Church power needfull to be exerciſed within it ſelf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently be independent from any other Church or Synods in the uſe of it; yet it is lawful, yea it is an uſeful, ſafe and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and holy Ordinance of Chriſt, and in ſome caſes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſuch particular Churches to joyn together in holy covenant or communion and conſotiation <hi>(ſo I think it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the Author, though the printed copy ſay conſolation)</hi> amongſt themſelves to adminiſter all their Church affairs which are of weighty and difficult and common concernment, not without common conſultation and conſent of other Churches about them. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline, preface A.</hi> 3. <hi>Mr. Cotton of the Keys pag.</hi> 54. <hi>line</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Why do ſome ſay this conſotiation of Churches is, uſeful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The conſotiation of Churches is not onely lawful but uſeful, ſerving not alone to ſearch out the truth, but to ſettle the hearts of all that are ſincerely minded in a right apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Hooker Survey of diſcipline, part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>When many, and thoſe ſelect and eminent, lay the beſt of their abilities together, improve their parts and prayers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, conſultations, determinations to promote the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115279:31"/>knowledge and practice of the things of Chriſt, the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churches in the unity of the faith and their eternal peace. Mr. <hi>Hooker Survey of diſcipline, part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Why do you ſay it is ſafe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſafe; for in the multitude of Councellers there is ſafety, as in civil ſo in Church affairs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.14. Mr. <hi>Cottons Keys pag.</hi> 55. <hi>line</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> The light of nature and right reaſon forceth men out of their own neceſſities and experiences to confeſs this that in multitude of Counſellers there is ſafety, <hi>Et plus vident oculi quam oculus,</hi> &amp;c. The iſſue of the Councel eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth as much, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.4, 5. They delivered the decrees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Churches were eſtabliſhed in faith. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline, part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>But if the Church be of a good and ſtrong conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and walk with a right foot in the truth and peace of the goſpel, what need of ſuch conſotiation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though this or that particular Church may be of a good and ſtrong conſtitution, and walk with a right foot in the truth and peace of the Goſpel;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi>
                  </note> yet all Churches are not in a like athletick plight, and they that are not ſo, will be loth to call in, or look out for help as much or more then others, though they have more need then others; yea and the beſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may ſoon degenerate and ſtand in as much need of help as others, and for want of it may ſink and fall into a deep Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, which other Churches might have prevented if they had diſcerned it at firſt. Mr. <hi>Cotton Keyes pag.</hi> 55. <hi>line</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Why do you ſay this combination and conſotiation of Churches is wholeſome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is wholeſome as tending to maintain brotherly love and ſoundneſs of doctrine in Churches,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and to prevent many offences which may grow up in this or that particular Church, when it tranſacts all ſuch things in it ſelf without con-Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes p.</hi> 55. <hi>line.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>But how do you prove it an Ordinance of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is an holy Ordinance of Chriſt as having juſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from a like precedent; the Apoſtles were as much inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent one from another,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and ſtood in as little need of help one from another, as Churches do. And yet <hi>Paul</hi> went up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to confer with <hi>Peter, Jam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> leſt he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115279:32"/>ſhould in vain run in the courſe of his Miniſtery, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.2. And though in conference the chief Apoſtles added nothing to <hi>Paul, ver.</hi> 6. yet when they perceived the Goſpel of uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was committed to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> as that of the circumciſion was to <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> they gave unto one another the right hand of fellowſhip. Now then it will follow by juſt proportion, that if the <hi>Apoſtl s</hi> who were <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent</hi> each of them one of another, had need to conſult and confer together, to procure a freer paſſage to their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to their doctrine; than ſurely <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>Elders of Churches,</hi> though <hi>independent</hi> one of another, had need to communicate te their courſes and proceedings in ſuch caſes one with another, to procure the freer paſſage to the ſame. And if the Apoſtles giving the right hand of fellowſhip one to another, did mutually ſtrengthen their hands in the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; then the Elders of Churches giving the right hand of fellowſhip one to another in their ordination, or upon any fit occaſion, cannot but much ſtrengthen the hearts and hands of one another in the Lords work. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys. page</hi> 55. <hi>line</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>Is there any thing which may be added, if not for confirmation, yet for illuſtration of the point.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, by comparing the dimenſion of the new <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> which is the perfect platforme of a pure Church, as it ſhall be conſtituted in the Jewiſh Church State at their laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> The dimenſions of this Church, as they are deſcribed by <hi>Ezekiel, chap.</hi> 48.30. are twelve furlongs, that is, about three miles in length, and as many in breadth. But the dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.16. is ſaid to be twelve thouſand furlongs. Now how can thoſe two dimenſions ſtand together, that are ſo far diſcrepant one from another, as twelve, and twelve thouſand? the fitteſt and faireſt reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation ſeems plainly to be this; that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaketh of the dimenſion of any ordinary Jewiſh Church of one particular Congregation, but <hi>John</hi> ſpeaketh of the dimenſion of many particular Jewiſh Churches combining together in ſome caſes, even to the communion of a thouſand Churches. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. page</hi> 56. <hi>line</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115279:32"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But <hi>Theologia Symbolica non eſt argumentativa; Arguments from Parables and myſtical reſemblances are not valid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there were no argumentative power in Parables,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> why did the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> delight ſo much in that kinde of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? and why did <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> deliver a great part of their Propheſies in Parables, if we muſt take them for Riddles, and not for Documents or Arguments? ſurely if they ſerve not for Arguments, they ſerve not for Documents. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. page</hi> 56. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>But is this Combination of Churches neceſſary, as well as lawful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Conſociation of Churches is not only lawful,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> but in ſome caſes neceſſary. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. preface. a.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nemo, inquit Parkerus, quod ſciam, Eccleſiae alicujus refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matae alumnus ante Hugonem Grotium negavit Synodos eſſe neceſſarias quibus nos <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> libenter profitemur.</hi> Norton <hi>adverſus Apollonium.</hi> pag. 112. Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> ſaith, that no man that was a Diſciple of the reformed Churches, did ever deny the neceſſity of Synods before <hi>Hugo Grotius;</hi> and we do unanimouſly confeſſe the neceſſity of them. Mr. <hi>Norton a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Apollonius. page</hi> 112. <hi>line</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>How many ſorts and degrees of Conſociation of Churches are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Conſociation is of ſeveral ſorts and degrees, ſome leſſer, ſome greater, as Claſſes, Synods,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> and theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, National and Oecumenical; thus farre we agree. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of Diſcipline. part</hi> 4. <hi>page</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 15. <hi>and</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>What is a Synod?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Synods we acknowledge being rightly ordered, as an Ordinance of Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Cottons Keyes. page</hi> 23. <hi>line</hi> 21. And though not abſolutely neceſſary to the being,<note place="margin">Platform of Diſcipline.</note> yet many times neceſſary to the well-being of Churches. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E. chap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>How is a Synod to be compoſed, and of what Members ought it to conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115279:33"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it is difficult, if not impoſſible, for many Churches to come altogether in one place,<note place="margin">Platform of Diſcipline.</note> in all their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers univerſally; therefore they may aſſemble by their delegates or meſſengers, as the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> went not all to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> but ſome ſelect men for that purpoſe; becauſe none are, or ſhould be more fit to know the ſtate of the Churches, nor to adviſe of wayes for the good thereof than Elders; therefore it is fit that in the choice of the meſſengers for ſuch Aſſemblies, they have ſpecial reſpect unto ſuch; yet, in as much as not only <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> but certain others alſo were ſent to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from <hi>Antioch,</hi> Acts 15. and when they were come to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not only the Apoſtles and Elders, but other Brethren alſo do aſſemble and meet about the matter, therefore Synods are to conſiſt both of Elders and other Church-members, endued with gifts, and ſent by the Churches, not excluding the preſence of any Brethren in the Churches. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline chap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>Whether may there be called and k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt a National Synod or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may ſo fall out that the State of all the Churches in the Country may be corrupted,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and beginning to diſcern their corruption, may deſire the concourſe and counſel of one another for a ſpeedy and ſafe, and general reformation; and then ſo meeting, all conferring together, may renew their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and conclude and determine upon a courſe that may tend to the healing and ſalvation of them all: this was frequent in the Old Teſtament in the time of <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah;</hi> theſe and the like examples were not peculiar to the Iſraelites as one intire National Church; theſe examples hold forth no ſuperiority in one Church or Court over another, but all of them in an equal manner give advice in common, and therefore ſuch examples are fit precedents for Churches of equal power within themſelves, to aſſemble together and take order with one accord for the Reformation of them all. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. pag.</hi> 24 <hi>l.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 13. <hi>But what is the work that properly belongs to Synods?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It belongs unto Synods and Councels to debate and determine controverſies of faith and caſes of conſcience,<note place="margin">Platforin of Diſcipline.</note> to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115279:33"/>clear from the Word holy directions for the holy worſhip of God, and good government of the Church, to bear witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt male-adminiſtration, and corruption of doctrine and manners in any particular Church, and to give direction for the Reformation thereof. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from N. E. chap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>In any part of the Churches way,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> which is more hard to hit right upon, as in Elections, Ordinations and cenſures of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons in office, it is a ſafe and holy faithful office of the vigilancy of the community of Churches, to be preſent with them, and helpful to them in the Lord; and at all times, when a particular Church ſhall wander out of the way, whither out of the way of truth or peace, the community of the Churches may by no means be excuſed from reforming them again into their right way according to the authority which the Lord hath given them for the publick edification of all the ſeveral Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es within their Covenant. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. page</hi> 58. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>What is then that power or authority which Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Combinations of Churches have in theſe caſes? is it only declarative and directive, or conſultative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We dare not ſay that their power reacheth no further than giving counſel;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> for ſuch as their ends be for which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God they do aſſemble, ſuch is the power given them of God as may attain thoſe ends. As they meet to miniſter light and peace to ſuch Churches, as through want of light and peace lye in error (or doubt at leaſt) and variance; ſo they have power by the grace of Chriſt, not only to give light and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in matter of truth and practice, but alſo to command and injoyn the things to be believed and done. The expreſſe words of the Synodal Letter imply no leſſe, It ſeemeth good to the Holy Ghoſt and us to lay upon you no other burden; this burden therefore to obſerve theſe neceſſary things which they ſpeak of, they had power to impoſe; it is an act of the binding power of the Keyes to binde burdens; and this binding ariſeth not only materially, from the weight of the matters impoſed, (which are neceſſary, <hi>neceſſitare praecepti,</hi> from the Word) but alſo formally, from the authority of the Synod, which being the Ordinance of Chriſt, binds the more for the Synods ſake.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115279:34"/>As a truth of the Goſpel taught by a Miniſter of the Goſpel, it bindeth to faith and obedience, not only becauſe it is Goſpel, but alſo becauſe it is taught by a Miniſter for his Callings fake; and ſurely alſo a Synod ſometimes meeteth to convince and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and offending Church or Presbytery; they have power (if they cannot heal the offenders) to determine to withdraw communion from them; and further, ſeeing they meet like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſometimes for general Reformation, they have power to decree and publiſh ſuch Ordinances as may conduce according to God to ſuch Reformation, examples whereof we have, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.32, 39. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12, 13. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys. page</hi> 25. <hi>line</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>How farre then are particular Churches bound to ſubmit themſelves to the directions or decrees of Synods?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Particular Churches are ſo far ſubject to the Conſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Churches,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
                  </note> that they are bound in caſe of doubt and difficulty to crave their counſel, and if it be according to God to follow it; or if the particular Churches erre from the rule, and continue obſtinately therein, the Conſociation have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to renounce the right hand of fellowſhip. Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey. part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 80. <hi>line</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>The Synods directions and determinations ſo far as conſonant to the Word of God, are to be received with reverence and ſubmiſſion; not only for their agreement therewith, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily for the power whereby they are made, as being an Ordinance of God appointed thereunto in his Word. <hi>Platforme of Diſcipline from New England. chap.</hi> 16. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Particular Churches are bound to acquieſce in the lawful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Synods received by the major part of the Churches, and approved by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. Mr. <hi>Nortons anſw. to Apollonius. page</hi> 118. <hi>line</hi> 3. And this, 1. Under the danger of incurring the guilt of diſturbing the order of the Church. 2. Under the penalty of non-communion by the reſt of the Churches. 3. Under the penalty of civil puniſhment to be inflicted by the Magiſtrate, as the matter ſhall require. Mr. <hi>Norton, ib. l.</hi> 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. 16. <hi>But hath the Synod authority to determine or conclude any thing that ſhall binde the Churches, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115279:34"/>to the inſtruction which they have received before from the Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not ſo apprehend it; for what need Churches ſend to a Synod for light and direction in ways of truth and peace, if they be reſolved before hand how far they will go? but if the Elders be gathered in the Name of Chriſt in a Synod, and proceed according to rule the (Word) of Chriſt, they may conſider and conclude ſundry points expedient for the eſtate of their Churches, which the Churches were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant or doubtful of before. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keys. pag.</hi> 26. <hi>line</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 17. <hi>But what if the Synod conclude and determine againſt the truth, and the Church ſtand for the truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is not readily to be granted (though neither is it ſimply to be denyed) that in Reformed times,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Norton.</hi>
                  </note> the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a particular Church ſhould be more ſound than the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Synod.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it is in civil things, there is an abſolute truth, and there is a judicial truth; and the ſentence of the ſupreme civil Judge, (ſuppoſe the Parliament) is true <hi>quoad homines,</hi> though it be not abſolutely true; ſo it is in Eccleſiaſtical things; the Synod being the ſupreme and higheſt Judge of the queſtion, the ſentence of the Synod, though it be not abſolutely true, yet it is Eccleſiaſtically true. <hi>Scil. in foro exteriore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Although, the truth after ſome new decrees of a new Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, repealing the act of the former, may remain with the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If the error be not fundamental, publick order is to be preferred before obedience to an affirmative precept that is not fundamental; though therefore a hoof of truth is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the liberties and lives of the ten thouſands of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> yet when the whole community is more endangered by the want of publick order, than by the preſent not obſerving of ſome affirmative command not fundamental, we ought to have more regard to publick order, than to the preſent obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſuch a command.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Therefore the particular Church in this caſe may and ought to ſubmit it ſelf to ſuch order, but yet without ſin. Mr. <hi>Nortons anſw. to Apollonius. pag.</hi> 118.119.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115279:35"/>Queſt. 18. <hi>But how can that been done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The truth is not to be diſſembled,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Norton.</hi>
                  </note> but the Church is modeſtly and peaceably to bear witneſſe to the truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Effor is never to be approved though for awhile, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the iniquity of the time it is to be tolerated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Wiſely and patiently we muſt wait in our ſtations in the due uſe of means, till God in his own proper ſeaſon ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the truth. Mr. <hi>Norton againſt Apollonius. page</hi> 119. <hi>line</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 19. <hi>Have all the Members of a Synod equal power?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Synod conſiſting,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> as we have heard it doth, of Elders and Brethren, their power is not the ſame, but diſtinct; the power which the Brethren have, it is a power of liberty; the power which the Elders have, it is a power of authority. The Brethren have firſt liberty to diſpute their doubts modeſtly and Chriſtianly among the Elders; ſo in that Synod at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Acts 15.7, 12. Secondly, they had liberty to joyne with the Apoſtles and Elders in determining the ſame, as the common ſenſe of them all. Thirdly, they had liberty to joyn with the Apoſtles and Elders in chooſing and ſending Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and in writing Synodal letters in the name of all, for the publiſhing of the ſentence of the Synod, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. to 29. But the authority of the decrees lay chiefly, if not only, in the Apoſtles and Elders, as appears, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.4. So then it will be moſt ſafe to preſerve to the Church of Brethren their due liberty, and to the Church of the Elders their due authority. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the Keyes. page</hi> 26. <hi>line</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 20. <hi>Whether may a perſon or perſons wronged by particular Churches, appeal to a Synod or no for redreſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a right of appeals in weighty cauſes from an inferior to a ſuperior ſentence.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Norton.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing that in Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, and among Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical perſons many differences do ariſe, who can deny but that this right of appeals muſt be granted there?</p>
               <p>Appeals are of divine and natural right, and neceſſary in all ſocieties, becauſe of the ignorance and unrighteouſneſſe of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115279:35"/>many who are Judges. Mr. <hi>Nortons anſwer to Apoll.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 112. <hi>line antepenult. &amp; page</hi> 114.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of the Combination or Conſociation of Churches, and of Synods, and their power. Now from theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars that have been delivered, let us draw ſome poſitions with their inferences.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, it is lawful for particular Churches to joyne together in a holy Covenant and communion amongſt themſelves to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter all Church Affairs of weight and difficulty, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concernment, not without common conſultation and conſent about them. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 1. Hence it follows,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That if an expreſſe conſent and Covenant be the <hi>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ratio,</hi> and conſtitutive of a Church; then theſe particular Churches thus joyned together, make up one Church; not <hi>repreſentativè &amp; impropriè,</hi> but truly and properly, having the true <hi>formale</hi> of a Church, and that which <hi>dat eſſentiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If they have thus covenanted together to tranſact things by common conſent, then every Church of the Conſociation hath the ſame power in all matters that the fraternity of a particular Church hath, to wit, of conſenting or of diſſenting.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If they Covenant to adminiſter all their affairs not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out common conſent, then quere whether every particular Church hath not a negative voice, which is more then the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians contend for.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If they Covenant to adminiſter all matters of weight and common concernment, NOT without common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, then the excommunication of any perſon being a matter of weight, (as doubtleſſe the delivering up of a ſoul to Satan is) and alſo a matter of common concernment, (he that is caſt out of one Church, being caſt out of all) will it not from the conceſſion follow that no particular Church can excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a Member, without the conſent of the aſſociated Churches?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This Conſociation of Churches, is ſafe, uſeful and wholeſome, and in ſome caſe neceſſary. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115279:36"/>2.3, 5, 8. they therefore who refuſe to aſſociate with other Churches when it is offered, let theſe conſider whether they do not forſake their own mercies.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Even the ſtrongeſt and beſt Churches have need of Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation; firſt, that they may help the weak; for all Churches are not in a like athletick plight; and ſecondly, for themſelves; for the beſt may ſoon degenerate, and for want of Aſſociation, may ſink and fall into deep Apoſtaſie. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 4. therefore,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe Aſſociations ought not to be elective; for then the ſtrong and athletick Churches may combine together, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the weaker and leſſe athletick, ſaying, we have no need of you; which would fruſtrate the end of combination; and therefore the beſt way is for Churches that are in vicinity to combine together.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the ſtrongeſt Church may need Conſociation to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent degeneration and Apoſtaſie, then the beſt way is to have theſe Conſociations fixed and ſtated, not occaſional only, <hi>&amp; pro re nata.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>— Sero med cina paratur,</l>
                     <l>Quum mala per long as invaluere moras.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="4">4. Combination of Churches is an holy Ordinance of Chriſt. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 6. Therefore let them conſider how they will anſwer it to Jeſus Chriſt, who not only live without this Ordinance, but deſpiſe it, and ſpeak evil of it, and yet have covenanted to walk in all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and would be thought ſo to do.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Combination of Churches is no more deſtructive to the power of particular Churches, than the Conſociation of the Apoſtles was to their Apoſtolical power. <hi>See anſwer to queſt.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. As the Apoſtles giving the right hand of fellowſhip one to another, ſtrengthened their hands in the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; ſo the Elders of Churches giving the right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip one to another upon any fit occaſion, cannot but ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the heart and hands of one another in the Lords work. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 7. Therefore for the Elders of Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115279:36"/>Churches to refuſe to aſſociate with their brethren of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother judgment, and to refuſe to give them the right hand of fellowſhip, what doth it declare but this, that either they do not think we in our Miniſtery work the work of the Lord, or elſe that they are reſolved to weaken our hands, and hinder our work as much as they can, becauſe though we do Gods work, yet we do not do it in their ways?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. A Combination of Churches, or a Claſſical Church, is a pure Goſpel Church, according to the moſt perfect platform; it is the new <hi>jeruſalem</hi> that came down from heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.16. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 7. therefore they are much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that ſay it is an Antichriſtian platform.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Claſſes and Synods Provincial and National are lawful, and warrantable. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 9. therefore they exceedingly prevaricate, who go about to render them either ridiculous as ſome, or odious as others.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. A Synod is an Ordinance of Chriſt, neceſſary, though not to the being, yet to the well-being of Churches. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 10. therefore it is as neceſſary as the reſt of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, which is neceſſary only for the well-being of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, not to their being. And ſecondly, therefore it is no more improper to have Combinations or Synods fixed and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than it is to have other meetings for Diſcipline ſo fixed.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Delegation to be a member of a Synod, is a lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-employment. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. All the Churches of a Nation may meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to conſult, and to renew their Covenant for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; if the Covenant conſtitute the Church, <hi>quere,</hi> whither they be not now a National Church? <hi>See anſw. to quest.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The practice of the Church in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> dayes, and in <hi>Joſiahs</hi> dayes, is a preſident for National Synods and Councils. <hi>See anſw. to quest.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Synods are uſeful, and have power in caſes of difficulty, and in ſuch caſes particular Churches are bound to make uſe of them. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 15. and in caſe of male-adminiſtration, and in ſuch caſes the Conſociated Churches are bound to take cognizance of it, &amp; redreſſe it. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115279:37"/>14. Synods have power and authority from Chriſt, not only to direct and give counſel, and declare the minde of Chriſt, but alſo to command and injoyne. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 19.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Synods have ſome part of the binding power of the Keyes. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 14. <hi>Quere,</hi> why not all as well as ſome, and where Chriſt hath made the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. The decrees and injunctions of Synods ſo far as they are agreeable to the Word of God, binde not only materially, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are agreeable to the Word, but formally, becauſe they are the decrees of a Synod, which is the Ordinance of Chriſt. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 14. <hi>and</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. In the determination of the major part of a Synod, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, particular Churches are bound to acquieſce upon pain 1. Of being guilty of diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the order and peace of the Church. 2. Of non-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 3. Of puniſhment by the Magiſtrate. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 15. if ſo, then firſt, the Magiſtrate may uſe compulſion and coercion in matter of Religion. Secondly, the vote of the major part of the late Aſſembly at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> had more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging power than ſome body would own, and ſome body is guilty of ſomething.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. The decrees of Synods though erroneous, yet, if not fundamentally erring, are not to be rejected or ſcorned, but received and ſubmitted to, rather than peace and order diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 17. If I underſtand this aright, our brethren ſay as much as can be deſired, if not more; O that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing near this had been practiſed!</p>
                  <p n="19">19. It is not eaſily to be granted that Synods erre, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons and Churches that are contrary-minded have the truth. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Appeals are warrantable by the Law of God, and the Law of nature, and neceſſary in all Societies, becauſe of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or iniquity of them that are Judges. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 20. therefore great is either their ignorance or their iniquity, who deny the members of their ſociety this juſt and neceſſary liberty of appeals.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115279:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Communion with, and Separation from the true Church.</head>
               <p>Queſtion 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHether there is an univerſal viſible Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Platform of Diſcipline.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There may be acknowledged an univerſal viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>What relation or reſpect do particular viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bear to the univerſal viſible Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Congregational Church by the inſtitution of Chriſt, is a part of the militant viſible Church. <hi>Platform of Diſcipline,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Platform of Diſcipline.</note> 
                  <hi>ſect.</hi> 6. This Catholick Myſtical Church is the <hi>Materia prima,</hi> out of which Political Churches by their combination are form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Defence of the</hi> 9. <hi>poſitions, pag.</hi> 104. The Catholick Church is in ſome reſpects the firſt Church, and particular Churches <hi>ortae. Ibid. pag.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Is every particular perſon bound to be of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every faithful perſon is bound by vertue of poſitive precept to joyn himſelf to ſome ſuch ſingle congregation,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Owen.</hi>
                  </note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the markes and notes by which a true Church may be known and diſcerned. Dr. <hi>Owen in his Eſhcol, Preface A</hi> 3. It is the part of all Chriſtians who look for ſalvation by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, to joyn themſelves to one or other particular Church of Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Cotton of the way,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>But is a man bound to joyn himſelf to the Church of that place where his dwelling is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Members ought to joyn themſelves to the Church where they do inhabit, if it may be;<note place="margin">Platform of Diſcipline.</note> otherwiſe they can neither perform the duties nor receive the priviledges of members; ſuch an example tolerated in ſome, is apt to corrupt others, which if they ſhould follow, would threaten the confuſion and diſſolution of Churches, contrary to Scripture. <hi>Platform of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All believers of one place are bound to joyn together in one congregation, unleſs through their being too numerous
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115279:38"/>they are by common conſent diſtinguiſhed into more, which order cannot be diſturbed without the guilt of ſchiſme. Dr. <hi>Owens Eſhcol Prefao? A.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>But is a man bound after he hath once joyned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a Church, to continue a member of this Church all his dayes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Church-members may not remove and depart from the Church,<note place="margin">Platform Diſcipline.</note> and ſo one from another as they pleaſe, but ought to dwell together. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Peoples joyning with a Pariſh at the calling and electing of a Miniſter at his firſt coming, hath ſuch juſt weight in it, and is ſuch an engagement, as we do not judge it ſafe for ſuch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from ſuch a Miniſter, unleſs it be upon ſuch grounds as may give him due ſatisfaction. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, Preface pag.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſeparate from a Church, either out of contempt of their holy fellowſhip, or out of covetuouſneſs, or for greater enlargements, with juſt grief to the Church, or out of Schiſme, or want of love, or out of a ſpirit of contention in reſpect of ſome unkindneſs, or ſome evil onely conceived, or indeed in the Church which might and ſhould be tolerated and healed with a ſpirit of meekneſs, and of which the Church is not yet convinced, though perhaps himſelf be, nor admoniſhed from theſe or like reaſons to withdraw from publike communion in word or ſeals, or cenſures, is unlawful and ſinful. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, cap.</hi> 13. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>But what if there be many wicked and ſcandalous perſons, and the Church tolerate them in it, ought not the godly to withdraw and depart from ſuch a Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To ſeparate from a Church for want of ſome Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or to ſeparate from the true worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> becauſe of the ſin of ſome worſhippers, is unlawful, Mr. <hi>Hookers Survey of diſcipline, Preface A.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſuffering of profane and ſcandalous livers to continue in the Church, and partake in the Sacrament, is doubtleſs a great ſin; yet the godly are not preſently to ſeparate from it, nor to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſtain from communion with ſuch a Church in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Sacrament. <hi>Platforme of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115279:38"/>3. The hypocriſie of ſundry members of the Church, and toleration of ſome open ſcandal doth not preſently take away the nature of the Church, nor is ſeparation preſently to be made from it. Mr. <hi>Cotton of holineſs of Church members, pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Chriſt and his Apoſtles in their times, and the Prophets and other godly in theirs did lawfully partake of the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Ordinances in the Jewiſh Church, and never taught nor practiſed ſeparation from the ſame, though unworthy ones were permitted to be therein. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8. And the Apoſtles kept communion with the Jews as a Church, notwithſtanding their want of faith in Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton of Infant Bapt. pag.</hi> 56. <hi>line</hi> 28. And the faithful in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> wherein were many unworthy perſons and practiſes, are never commanded to abſent themſelves from the Sacrament becauſe of the ſame; therefore the godly in like cauſes are not preſently to ſeparate. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, chap.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>But if I can go to a Church that is more pure, and where things are better ordered, and more according to the minde of Chriſt, why may I not leave communion with one Church and go to another? As ſuppoſe I think the Congregational Churches purer then the Presbyterian, may I not leave the Presbyterian and joyn to the Congregational?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not judge it ſafe or meet for any member of a Presbyterian Church,<note place="margin">Platforme of Diſcipline.</note> forthwith to deſert his relation to his Church, and betake himſelf to the fellowſhip of a congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church, though he may diſcern ſome defect in the eſtate and government of his own.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For firſt, Faithfulneſs of brotherly love in Church relation requires that the members of the Church ſhould firſt convince their brethren of their ſinful defects, and duely wait for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation before they depart from them; for if we muſt take ſuch a courſe for the healing of a private brother, by way of brotherly love, with much meekneſs and patience; how much more ought we to walk with like tenderneſs towards the whole Church?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, By the haſty departure of ſound members from a defective Church; reformation is not promoted, but many
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115279:39"/>times retarded and corruption increaſed: whereas on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry when ſincere members breathing after purity of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abide together, they may by the bleſſing of God upon their faithful endeavors prevail much with their elders and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors towards a reformation; it may be ſo much that their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in their own Church ſhall receive none to the ſeals but viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Saints; and in the Claſſes ſhall put forth no authoritative act touching the members of other Churches, but conſultative onely, nor touching their own, but with the conſent (ſilent conſent at leaſt) of their own Church; which two things if they can obtain with any holy, humble, meek, faithful endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, we conceive they might by the grace of Chriſt find liberty of conſcience to continue their relation to their own Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Churches without ſcruple. <hi>Platform of diſcipline, preface pag.</hi> 5. <hi>line</hi> I.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But we ſcruple not onely theſe but many other things: As firſt, Your Miniſters many of them had their Ordination from the Biſhops, and they theirs from</hi> Rome, <hi>and ſo your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery is Antichriſtian; and thoſe that are not ordained by Biſhops are Ordained by a Claſſis or Presbytery, which is a power forreign and extrinſecal to the Church whoſe Miniſters they are?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, For the Miniſters that were ordained by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, take it thus.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> The power whereby the Miniſters in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land do adminiſter the Word and Sacraments, is either ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and proper, eſſential to their calling, or adventitious or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental. The former they have received from Chriſt by a twofold act of his. Firſt, He hath furniſhed many of them with mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial gifts. Secondly, He hath enclined the hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to chooſe them, and call them as in many Pariſhes in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in ſundry Market-Towns and elſewhere, or at leaſt to accept them, and ſubmit to them, being commended to them by the Patron.</p>
               <p>The latter power which is adventitious and accidental, that which they receive from the Patron who preſents them to the Biſhop, and from the Biſhop who ordains and licenſeth them to Miniſter to Chriſt, and to his people; This power though it hath been eſtabliſhed by the Law of the Land, yet it is both ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious and accidental; for the Miniſters power is compleat
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115279:39"/>without it, and it is alſo uſurped; For neither had the law law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful power from Chriſt to give ſuch power to the Patron and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop neither had the Biſhop or Patron lawful power to receive it, neither could the people then chooſe their Miniſter without the leave of their Patron, nor induct him into the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ordination or leave of the Biſhop. Thus when Pyrates have invaded a ſhip, no man in it, neither Officer nor Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger can come by his own goods, but by leave of the Pyrate, who upon their ſubmiſſion will give them their keyes of their own veſſels and cheſts; this power to come to their own goods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Pyrate, it is not that which gives them true and proper right to enter upon the poſſeſſion and uſe of their own goods; for that right they had by a former juſt title which Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates cannot diſannull,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> but it is onely adventitious and accident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. I need not apply it to the caſe in hand; the application is obvious. Mr. <hi>Cotton of Infant Bapt. pag.</hi> 181. <hi>line</hi> 25. And as for thoſe Miniſters that are ordained by Claſſes or Presbyteries, as you call them; I anſwer, firſt, Ordination is a work of rule and pertains to Presbyters. Mr. <hi>Cotton way of the Churches, pag.</hi> 49. <hi>line</hi> 4. And ſecondly, In ſuch Churches where there are no Elders, and the Church ſo deſires, we ſee not why impoſition of hands may not be performed by the Elders of other Churches. <hi>Platform of Diſcipline from N.E. chap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>May then we who are members of gathered or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Churches, hear their Miniſters as Miniſters of the Goſpel, and hold communion with them in their Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We may hold and retain communion with them in baptizing our children (as occaſion may fall out by abſence of our Miniſters) in their Churches,<note place="margin">Apologetical Narration. They ſay but do not, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> and by occaſional receiving the Supper of the Lord in their Churches, and receiving ſuch mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of theirs <hi>as are duly qualified</hi> unto communion with us oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally; alſo our Miniſters to preach in their Congregations, and receive theirs alſo to preach in ours as Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. Papers given to the Committee of accommodation, by <hi>Thomas Goodwin, Philip Nye, William Bridge, Sydrach Simſon, Ierom. Burroughs, pag.</hi> 29. <hi>line</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>What ſhall we judge then of the Separatiſts or Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts? are they of Antichriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sure their practice is blame worthy:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115279:40"/>1. Becauſe they ſeparate where Chriſt keeps fellowſhip, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18. and that he walks with us we argue,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe he is ſtill pleaſed to diſpenſe to us the word of life, and edifies many ſouls thereby; and therefore ſurely Chriſt hath fellowſhip with us; and ſhall man be more pure then his Maker? where Chriſt vouchſafes fellowſhip, ſhall man renounce it? if they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, where had they their converſion?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Have not many of Gods ſervants heretofore kept com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with Churches as corrupt as ours are? did not <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> keep company with their perſons, and ſhall they be more pure and curious?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſt commands, if thy brother offend thee, admoniſh him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then tell it to the Church; and if he hear not the Church, let him be unto thee as a heathen or a publican, he doth not ſay let the Church be unto the as a heathen or a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican if the Church hear not thy complaint. Now there are many of our Separatiſts never admoniſh their brethren, nor made their complaint to the Church; and if they did, and the Church heard them not, muſt they therefore excommunicate the Church and renounce it? Therefore unleſs you finde in it blaſphemy, or idolatry, or perſecution, there is no juſt ground of ſeparation. Mr. <hi>Cottons expoſition of the firſt epiſtle of</hi> John, <hi>fol.</hi> 156. <hi>l.</hi> 38.</p>
               <p>Object. I. <hi>They ſay our worſhip is corrupt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe there were and are ſundry abuſes in the Church,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> yet that is no ſafe ground of ſeparation, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. So when the ſons of <hi>Eli</hi> corrupted the ſacrifices of God, their ſin was great; yet it was the ſin of the people to ſeparate and abhor, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17. Mr. <hi>Cottons Expoſition of the firſt epiſtle of</hi> John, <hi>fol.</hi> 157. <hi>line</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Object. 2 <hi>They ſay our government is Antichriſtian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſay it is that Government that expelled Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and ſundry have witneſſed it with their blood; and I ſay further, That there is no ſuch corruption in our ſtate as was in Jeruſalem, when Chriſt and his Apoſtles kept fellowſhip with them, as two high Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c. Ibid. line</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Obj. 3. <hi>They ſay our Miniſtry and Calling is Antichriſtian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſay we do not profeſs our ſelves enemies to Chriſt;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> and for our Calling, many of us are elected by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples approbation, or by ſuch as are ſet up by the King or State,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115279:40"/>and if God bleſs our Miniſtry to convert thouſands to God, it is an evident ſign God approves our Calling; for if it were Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, they would not convert ſouls unto God. <hi>Ibid. line</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>They ſay our people are corrupt, and ſome ſuch as</hi> Paul <hi>bids not to have communion with,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.11. <hi>as drunkards whoremongers and the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We cannot deny but that there are very many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſcandalous perſons in our Church: But,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Private Chriſtians have no authority to put them out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Miniſters, if they ſee it would turn to the diſſipation and deſtruction of the flock, it were better to forbear, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.29, 30. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4.20. they ceaſed from building the Temple, when there came a command againſt it;<note place="margin">O that you were wiſe to conſider theſe things!</note> therefore they had better forbear when it cannot be redreſſed without greater prejudice to the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The corruption of ſome doth not corrupt the Church nor the ordinances of God; he that eates and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks damnation to himſelf, not to the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; and you ſhall finde many Churches as corrupt, as the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> yet the Apoſtle would not have them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it. Mr. <hi>Cottons expoſition of the firſt epistle of</hi> John, <hi>fol.</hi> 157. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of communion with and ſeparation from the Church, now to draw ſome poſitions from theſe particulars, with ſome inferences upon them.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There may be acknowledged an univerſal viſible Church, which is the <hi>materia prima</hi> of particular Political Churches, and may in ſome reſpects be called the firſt Church, and particular Churches <hi>ortae. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to firſt and ſecond queſtion.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Catholike viſile Church is not a <hi>Chimaera,</hi> nor a chief pillar of Popery, as ſome pleaſe to ſpeak.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Every faithful perſon, yea every one that looketh for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt, is bound to joyn himſelf to ſome or other particular Church of Chriſt. <hi>See anſw. to queſt.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome or other particular Church is bound to receive every one that looks for ſalvation by Chriſt, and deſires to joyn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115279:41"/>unto them; for to ſay that every Chriſtian is bound to joyn himſelf to ſome particular Church, and yet no Church bound to receive him, is to lay an impoſſible obligation upon a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All the believers of one place (be it Town, Village, or Pariſh) are bound to joyn together in one Church, and this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cannot be diſturbed without guilt of Schiſme; and it is moſt for edification for men to be of the Church that is in the place where they dwell. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 4. Therefore the practice of thoſe who gather into one Church members dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in three, four or ſix ſeveral places diſtant many miles each from other, tends not to edification, nor cannot be excuſed from guilt of Schiſm.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Peoples joyning with a Pariſh in chooſing and calling a Miniſter, is ſuch an engagement as it is not ſafe for ſuch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from ſuch a Miniſter, but upon ſuch grounds as may give him due ſatisfaction. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 5. Therefore they have provided but an uneaſie pillow for themſelves to lay their heads on another day, who have caſt off thoſe Miniſters with contempt and ſcorn (to the breaking and ſadding of their hearts) whom themſelves choſe and called, as moſt of the members of the gathered Churches (ſo called) throughout <hi>England</hi> have done.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. To ſeparate from a Church, either out of contempt of their holy fellowſhip, or out of covetouſneſs, or for greater enlargements with juſt grief to the Church, or out of Schiſme, or for want of love, or out of a ſpirit of contention in reſpect of ſome unkindneſs or ſome evil onely conceived, or which might be tolerated and healed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſinful and unlawful. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>queſt.</hi> 5. <hi>anſw.</hi> 2. Therefore, O that thoſe who have rent themſelves from us, to gather themſelves into diſtinct Churches, would be wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ling to behold the face of what they have done, in, and judge it by this friendly glaſs, and repent of what they have done unlawfully and ſinfully!</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Neither the hypocriſie of ſome members, nor the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of open ſcandals, nor want of ſome Ordinances is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground for men to ſeparate from the Church. Therefore our brethren can alledge no ſufficient ground for their ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on from the Churches, whereof they were ſometimes mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115279:41"/>7. Faithfulneſs of brotherly love in Church relation, requires that the members of the Church ſhould, firſt convince their brethren of their ſinful defects, and duely wait for their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation before they depart from them. For ſecondly, By the haſty departure of ſound members from a defective Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is not promoted, but many times retarded. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 7. Therefore let thoſe who have ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Miniſtery and aſſemblies they did ſometimes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon, lay their hands upon their hearts, and ſeriouſly as before the Lord, conſider whether they have thus endevored and waited for a reformation in the Congregation where their fixed abode is, or whether they have not by their haſty depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (or by other indirect means) hindred the work of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as much as in them lies; the Lord lay it not to their charge. If for this they be not condemned by their own conſciences, I am ſure they are by their friends and brethren.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Ordination of Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> by the Biſhops, is adventitious and accidental to their calling. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>queſt.</hi> 7. <hi>anſwer to Object.</hi> 4. Therefore their ordination by the Biſhops doth not make their calling null and void; nor is it neceſſary that they ſhould renounce that call, and put themſelves upon a new call, unleſs withall they change their ſtation.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The difference between Independents and Presbyterians, is not ſo great, but that it might be healed, and there might a be an union, if ſome diſtempers and carnal corrupt reſpects did not prevail above principles of judgement and love to peace and truth. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 No juſt ground of ſeparation from a Church, unleſs you find in it blaſphemy, idolatry, or perſecution. <hi>See chap.</hi> 4. <hi>queſt.</hi> 9. <hi>anſw.</hi> 3. Therefore none of theſe crimes being proved againſt the Churches of <hi>England,</hi> they have done unjuſtly who have ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115279:42"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ANd now Brethren, If I could with <hi>Jotham</hi> get up into ſome Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> where I might be heard and not ſeen, or at leaſt where I might be <hi>extra jactum lapidum,</hi> I would ſpeak plainly to you, and not as he in parables: And I would numbly, and as in the ſight and fear of God deſire you to give (not me, but) the Chriſtian world, ſome conſcientious and ſatisfactory reaſon of your <hi>departing,</hi> and yet <hi>continuing</hi> ſo departed from the <hi>Churches,</hi> into which you were baptized, wherein you were converted (which reverend Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> is not aſhamed to own, ſaying, <hi>We cannot, we dare not deny to bleſs the wombe that bare us, and the paps that gave us ſucke,</hi> Mr. Cotton lett. print. A. 1641. pag. 3. line 27.) (the moſt of you that are converted) and whereof many of you were ſometimes <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> yet now you have not onely made a <hi>Negative ſeceſſion</hi> from them, but a poſitive: and have drawn and culled out of thoſe Congregations (whom yet you confeſs to be true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) as many of the choiceſt members as you could, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them (as you ſpeak) into Churches, not onely <hi>diſtinct</hi> from, but <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the Reſt of the Churches and Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Nation.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>oppoſite;</hi> for verily if you lived among Papiſts or Jews, you could ſcarce ſhew a greater oppoſition or abhorrence of their aſſemblies and worſhip, than you do of theſe. <hi>Some</hi> of you may be will hear <hi>ſome</hi> of their Miniſters <hi>ſometimes</hi> preach (though others of you will not vouchſafe that) ſo <hi>ſome</hi> of you have heard a <hi>Rabbi</hi> in a <hi>Jewiſh Synagogue;</hi> you know this is no act of Church communion, you know you hear them <hi>Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> not as <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt, but <hi>as gifted brethren.</hi> But who of you will break bread in their Aſſemblies, though the principal leaders of your way have given it under their hand (ſee Pap. of accommodat.) firſt to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſince
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115279:42"/>to the world, that they could do it? who of you will vouchſafe your preſence at the adminiſtration of Baptiſm in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, let it be the infant of never ſo holy parents, but make as much haſt out of their Aſſemblies, as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> did out of the <hi>Bath</hi> when he heard <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was in it? What is this but to lay all <hi>theſe Churches,</hi> and <hi>all the Members</hi> of them at leaſt under the ſentence of <hi>non communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for this practice I could never yet hear any thing alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but what is here fully anſwered and refelled out of your own Authors.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you ſay, <hi>Their Churches are no true Churches.</hi> See cap 3. per totum.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you ſay theſe Churches, <hi>they have not the matter of a true Church, which is viſible Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This hath been anſwered already: Firſt for the matter Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> hath told you, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>queſt.</hi> 1. <hi>That the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the New Teſtament conſiſt of no other matter than the Churches of the old conſiſted of;</hi> and what <hi>viſible Saints</hi> they were, the books of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles, Iſaiah, Ieremiah,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets tell you, <hi>That unregeneracy, unleſs it be accompanied with ſuch fruits as are openly ſcandalous, doth not keep any from Church fellowſhip.</hi> Anſw. to queſt. 3. cap. 1. <hi>that federal holineſs, or holineſs by ſeparation, admits to the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> cap. 1. queſt. 4. And <hi>that perſons who received their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip in their infancy, proving notoriouſly ſcandalous, ought not to be continued in Church-memberſhip, yet if they be, that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration must not preſently be made,</hi> is the judgement both of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hooker</hi> and the reſt of the Elders of New England. See this <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you ſay, <hi>Theſe Presbyterian Churches have not the right form and conſtitution, that is, expreſſe conſent and covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why this hath been anſwered; for Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> and Maſter <hi>Cotton,</hi> and the reſt of the Elders agree, that the <hi>Congregations of</hi> England <hi>have that which doth as truely conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute them Churches, as if they were conſtituted by covenant,</hi> as appears <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>anſwer to queſtion</hi> 4. See more <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If you ſay, <hi>In theſe Presbyterian Churches the Officers Lord it over the inheritance of the Lord, and rob and ſpoile the brethren of the power which Chriſt hath purchaſed for them, and bequeathed to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115279:43"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is clear by what hath been ſpoken already, that the brethren in the Congregational way have no more nor other power than what the brethren in the Presbyterian way; for M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cotton</hi> ſaith the power which the Brethren have, it is but a power of liberty, but the power of Authority is in the Elders. <hi>See cap.</hi> 5. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 14, 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you ſay, <hi>The brethren In the Presbyterian way have not ſo much liberty as in the congregational: For firſt they have not the liberty of exerciſing their gifts in prophecying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> and Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> both have told us how farre they are from allowing this liberty which ſome preſume to take to themſelves. See before <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> queſtion</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you ſay, <hi>They in the Presbytery have not that liberty of conſenting or diſſenting in the admiſſion of members, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational have, but the examination is taken in private by the Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So it is frequently in the Congregational Churches, and for ſome perſons conſtantly, as we have ſeen above <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>anſ. to queſt.</hi> 14, 15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you ſay, <hi>The brethren in the Presbyterian way have not the ſame liberty and power in cenſures that they have in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea the ſame; for the brethren in the Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way have not power to receive complaints in the firſt place, to hear and examine witneſſes; but theſe things are tranſacted before and among the Elders.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Elders they make reports of matters to the Church of brethren, and withall declare what they judge to be the mind of Chriſt concerning the cenſuring or not cenſuring of the perſon.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The people, they upon this relation judge of the whole, but with a judgement of diſcretion, not with a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Authority.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They thus judging, bind the offender by conſent, not Authority.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, This conſent is an act of obedience, not of power; all theſe we have ſeen clearly aſſerted <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>in anſw. to queſt.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Now all this the brethren may and do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy and exerciſe in the Presbyterian way.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115279:43"/>If you ſay, <hi>Brethren in the Presbyterian way cannot excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate without their Officers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No more may they in the Congregational way, as appeared <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>The Brethren of the Presbyterian way have not power to chooſe their own officers, as they have in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> According to the Presbyterian principles they have; and the practice is ſo in <hi>France, Netherlands Geneva, Scotland;</hi> and if it be otherwiſe in <hi>England,</hi> it is becauſe the laws of the land do yet inveſt the Patron with a power of nominating and preſenting a Miniſter; but the brethren have their vote in chooſing the other officers, Elders and Deacons; and the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian affirms, and they grant they ought to have it in the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their teaching Elders much more; beſides there are many inſtances of Presbyterian Congregations in <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere in <hi>England,</hi> that do chuſe their own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>The brethren of the Presbyterian way cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Miniſters or other officers, without the conſent of a Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis or Synod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No more may the brethren of the congregational way, regularly according to their own principles and aſſertions. <hi>See cap.</hi> 6. <hi>queſt.</hi> 1.13, 14.</p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>Theſe Presbyterian Churches have Ordinances that are not of Chriſts inſtitution: As,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They examine thoſe whom they admit to the Sacrament, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they own them for members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yet they nowhere ſay that this is an Ordinance of Chriſt, but a prudential practice, which the brethren of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational way own and practice as well as they. <hi>See cap.</hi> 4. <hi>anſw. to queſt.</hi> 14, 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you ſay, <hi>The Presbyterian Churches have ſuſpenſions of perſons not excommunicated as an Ordinance of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They own and uſe it no otherwiſe than the brethren of the Congregational way do, as appears <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>anſwer to queſt.</hi> 22, 23.</p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>They have Claſses and Synods as an Ordinance of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115279:44"/>I anſwer, The Congregational Churches own them for ſuch, and aſcribe more than a conſultative power to them. <hi>See cap.</hi> 6. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you except againſt the ordination of their Miniſters, <hi>See cap.</hi> 7. <hi>queſt.</hi> 7. <hi>anſw. to the objection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you ſay, <hi>Their-Churches are true Churches but not pure, you have purer Churches and purer ordinances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, Theſe are indeed the devices whereby people are drawn away from them to you; but I beſeech you tell us parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly what Ordinances have you purer then your brethren? Is the Word more purely preached amongſt you than amongſt them? came the Goſpel forth from you, or came it unto you onely? are there purer prayers and purer Sacraments amongſt you than amongſt them? do not they call upon the true Jehovah in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as you do, abhorring and renouncing all other objects and means of worſhip? do not they Baptize with water in the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, as you do? do not they break the ſame bread, and drink the ſame cup according to Chriſts inſtitution, in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of his death as you do? Where then, or what are theſe purer Ordinances which you have more than your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</p>
               <p>And for the purity of your Churches, I am loth to anſwer, as our Reformed Divines anſwered the like cavil of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts and Browniſts by Recrimination. Yet I think I may ſay, Are there not with you, even with you alſo ſinners againſt the Lord? but I will refer you for anſwer to your own friends, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>per totum, and cap.</hi> 7. <hi>queſt.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
               <p>And now brethren I beſeech you conſider the grounds upon which you have made, and do yet continue this ſad diviſion, and if you have no other than theſe, as I think you have not, let all the world judge whether they be not deſtroyed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by your own conceſſions.</p>
               <p>And let me be permitted to ſpeak to you once again in the words of <hi>Iotham,</hi> Hearken to me that God may hearken to you; you have been ſtudying the purity of Churches to the utmoſt <hi>apex</hi> of it (and it may be beyond) there may be a purity <hi>ſupra ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum</hi> as well as a devotion. But O that you would ſtudy the peace of Churches, and that not onely theſe of your own <hi>Idea
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115279:44"/>and Platform;</hi> but of all the Churches of Chriſt, I have heard ſome much complain of rigid Presbyterians: Do not you derive that title of rigid to your ſelves. The brethren of the Presbyterian way have ſufficiently declared their readineſſe to peace in their ſeveral models of aſſociation publiſhed by ſeveral Countries, to which theſe collections out of the Authors of the Congregational way, come ſo neer, that if you refuſe to come in and unite (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ſuch a time as this, when we have ſeen already ſuch ill fruits of our diviſions, and have cauſe to fear yet worſe) the rigidneſſe will lie at your door. Seeing your Brethren and you agree in faith and worſhip; why ſhould you live like <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> like <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papist,</hi> like <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts?</hi> Know you not it will be bitterneſſe in the end? Why, ſeeing your ſelves are convinced, and have declared, <hi>That Members of reforming Churches ought not to refuſe communion one with another, ſo far as may conſiſt with their principles reſpectively.</hi> And communion with Presbyterians may conſiſt with your principles, at leaſt it doth with the principles of theſe from whom you profeſſe to have received the principles of your way. Why ſhould ye yet abhorre their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? if you do, judge whether your own mouths and hands have not condemned you. Hearken therefore to me, that God may hearken unto you; or if you will not hearken unto me, yet heark to</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Irenaeus, lib. <hi>4.</hi> adv. haereſ. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </bibl> Probatio vera &amp; minime contradictioni obnoxia, quae etiam ab adversaries ipſis ſymbola teſtificationis profert, <hi>i. e.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Thats a true proof, and not to be contradicted, that brings forth the Teſtimonies even of the adverſaries.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hearken to</hi> Baſil, homil. in Chr. Nativ.</bibl> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>i.e.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>The witneſſes of adverſaries are moſt worthy of credit.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115279:45"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hearken to</hi> Chryſoſtome homil. <hi>82.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Iohan.</bibl> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <p>This is an unrefragable demonſtration of Truth, if a man call adverſaries to witneſs what he ſpeaks.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hearken to</hi> Cyprian de Uni. Eccleſ.</bibl> Quomodo poſſunt duo aut tres in nomine Christi colligi, quos conſtat a Chriſto &amp; ab ejus Evangelio ſeparari? non enim nos ab illis ſed illi a nobis receſſerunt. Et cum haereſes &amp; ſchiſmata poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modumnatae ſunt, dum conventicula ſibi diverſa conſtituunt, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis caput atque originem reliquerunt.</q>
               <p>i. e. How can two or three be gathered together in the name of Chriſt, when tis manifeſt they are ſeparated from Chriſt and from his Goſpel? for we have not departed from them, but they from us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hearken to</hi> Auſt. Epiſtola ad orthod. Con. Donat.</bibl> Quicunque de Chriſto &amp; ſcripturis ſanctis conſentiunt &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati Eccleſiae non communicant, non ſunt in Eccleſia.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Libr. <hi>3.</hi> Cont. Donat.</bibl> Non habet dei charitatem, qui Eccleſiae non diligit uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</q>
               <p>i.e. They that agree concerning Chriſt and the Scriptures, and do not communicate in the unity of the Church, are not in the Church.</p>
               <p>He hath not the love of God, who doth not love the Churches unity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115279:45"/>Hearken to <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>l Cor. 1.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Phil. 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and mercies;</p>
                  <p>Fulfill ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one minde.</p>
                  <p>Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain-glory, but in lowll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, let each eſteem other better than themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 5.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 9. line 3. read on, p. 22. l. 13. r. endued. p. 29. l. 24. r. Governors, p. 43. l. 35. r. this, p. 46. l. 36. r. or, p. 47. l. 32. r. conſotiation, p. 54. l. 1. r. be.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
